<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Testimony of some persecuted Presbyterian ministers of the Gospel unto the covenanted reformation of the Church of Scotland and to the present expediency of continuing to preach the Gospel in the fields and against the present antichristian toleration in its nature and design &amp;c. / given in to the ministers at Edenburgh by Mr. James Renwick upon the 17 Janwarii, 1688.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T818</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213976</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10772264</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10772264</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45791</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64458)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45791)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1412:1 or 1800:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Testimony of some persecuted Presbyterian ministers of the Gospel unto the covenanted reformation of the Church of Scotland and to the present expediency of continuing to preach the Gospel in the fields and against the present antichristian toleration in its nature and design &amp;c. / given in to the ministers at Edenburgh by Mr. James Renwick upon the 17 Janwarii, 1688.</title>
                  <author>Renwick, James, 1662-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Item at reel 1412:1 imperfect: last page cropped with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 1800:4 identified as Wing R1045 with a suggested Edinburgh imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in: Bodleian Library and New College (University of Edinburgh). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland.</term>
               <term>Presbyterian Church --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45791:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TESTIMONY, OF <hi>Some perſecuted Presbyterian Miniſters of the Goſpel, unto the Covenanted Reformation</hi> OF THE CHURCH of SCOTLAND, And to the preſent expediencie of continuing to preach the Goſpel in the Fields, and againſt the preſent Antichriſtian To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration in its nature and deſign, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Given in to the Miniſters at Edenburgh by</hi> Mr. JAMES RENWICK upon the 17. Janwarii 1688.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſ. 2.1.2.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Say ye unto your Brethren Ammi, and to your Siſters Ruhamah. Plead with your Mother, plead: for she is not my Wife neither am I her Husband: Let her therefore put away her whoredoms out of her ſight, and her adulteries from between her breaſts; Left I ſtirp her naked &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 58.1.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Cry aloud ſpare not, lift up thy voice like a Trumpet, and shew my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple their transgreſſion, and the Houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> their ſins. Yet they ſeek me daily and delight to know my ways, as a Nation that did righteouſneſs, and forſook not the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of their God; &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lamen. 2.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thy Prophets have ſeen vain and foolish things for thee, and they have not Diſcovered thine iniquitie, to turn away thy captivity, but have ſeen for thee falſe burthens, and cauſes of banishment.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 6.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They have healed alſo the hurt of the Daughter of my People ſlightly, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, peace, peace, when ther is no peace.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45791:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45791:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Christian and Candid Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SUch is the iniquity and unhappineſs of theſe times; wherein Judgment is turned away backward, and Juſtice ſtandeth afar off, Truth is falen in the ſtreets and equity can not enter, yea Truth faileth, and he that depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from evil maketh himſelf a prey, whereat the Lord is diſpleaſed, when he ſees there is no man, and Wonders there is no Interceſſor; That, now when the Caſe of Confeſſion is very clear and clamant, to aim at theſe indiſpenſible and ever heretofore indiſputable duties, of <hi>pleading for Truth, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Truth,</hi> being <hi>valiant</hi> for it, <hi>ſtanding in the Gap</hi> to turn away wrath, <hi>pleading with our Mother</hi> to put away her whoredomes, allways called for in ſuch a Caſe, is flouted at with diſdain and exploded with indignation, as a ridiculous imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency. And ſo declaredly are theſe duties declined, and ſo induſtriouſly are theſe declentions daubed, that the common dialect uſed and known among the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Chriſt is inverted, &amp; the very name and notion of theſe things profeſſedly perverted, under the interchanged deſignation of their oppoſite extreames: When now <hi>Tyranny</hi> paſſes under the name of <hi>Authority,</hi> and arbitrary <hi>abſolutneſs</hi> under the notion of Magiſtratical <hi>prerogative;</hi> Complyance with miſchiefs, framed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Laws by a Thron of inquity, goes for <hi>Loyaltie;</hi> Acceptance of a Popish, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion-undermining, Reformation-overturning, Liberty-perverting, Law-ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Truth-enſlaving <hi>Toleration,</hi> improving a <hi>Liberty</hi> to preach the Goſpel; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and shameful ſilence and unfaithfulneſs, paſſing over the indignites done unto Chriſt, His Cauſe and Covenants broken, burnt, and buried, and encro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>achments made upon His Kingly prerogatives, and Kingdoms Liberties, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a witneſs, is counted warry and witty <hi>prudence;</hi> ſtupid indifferency in the Lords matters, preferring their oun things to His, poſponing His precious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, to preſent eaſe, and ſelling Truth to purchaſe an unhallowed peace from and with Chriſts Enemies, is called and encouraged as <hi>moderation:</hi> On the other hand, To <hi>ſtand faſt in the Liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free,</hi> that is taken for licenciouſneſs; To maintain <hi>Religion</hi> with human <hi>Liberty,</hi> that is Rebellion; To ſtand at a diſtance from and withſtand theſe Land-defiling and deſtroying ſins, that is <hi>faction;</hi> To abſtract and abſtain from all acceſſion to ſaying <hi>a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy to all to whom the People ſay a Confederacy,</hi> for fear of the Lord, leſt the benefice of His ſanctuary be forfeited, that is <hi>ſchiſme</hi> and ſinfull <hi>ſeperation;</hi> To give every thing its owne name, in plainneſs and Goſpel ſimplicity, thats reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>railery,</hi> and pitiful ſillineſs; <hi>faithfulneſs,</hi> thats <hi>folly; zeal,</hi> thats <hi>wildneſs;</hi> Tenderneſs of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> thats ſuperſtitious and prepoſterous <hi>ſcrupuloſity;</hi> a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony can no ſooner be named, then it is ſuſpected of Giddineſs, hot headed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and preſently huffed and puffed at, caſt away and laid by, as an Ignorant, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, inſignificant ridicule. Under ſuch diſtempers and prejudices, it muſt needs be very difficult &amp; diſcouraging to offer a Teſtimony for the precious Truths
<pb facs="tcp:45791:3"/>of Chriſt; eſpecially for the hunted hiden ones, inceſſantly chaſed, continually purſued indefatigably perſecuted by the rage of enemies, contempt of friends, and reproach of alls; and Labournig under ſuch diſadvantages, that the ſenſe of their oune incapacity to exhibit it, with any ſuitablneſs to the matter and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, the want of the concurrence of thoſe that are better accomplished for it, little hope of the countenance of theſe that do not concurr, of acceptance with thoſe that do not give their countenance, or of acceſs to communicat it to thoſe that do not accept it (without expoſing themſelves to manifeſt Hazard) or of getting their help to publish it, to whom they dar not freely communicat it, can not but demur, dauntand diſcourage them from any ſuch eſſay. The fellowing Teſtimony was attended with thoſe diſadvantages; which contrary to the intention of the Authors, did both retard the publishing of it in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner firſt reſolved, and precipitate the printing of it in the preſent exigence. For it was firſt intended to have been given in to ſome ſolemn Meeting of Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Miniſters who preach under the preſent Toleration, that by them it might be communicated to whom they pleaſed, and Joyntly Cognoſced upon, and thoughts of it returned. But ſuch meetings being hid from us, and hardly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to perſons in our Circumſtances, the principle Author a faithfull Miniſter and now Glorified Matyr of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>James Renwick</hi> (now above the reach of rage and reproach, and Crowned with victory over ſin and ſorrow, pride of men &amp; ſtrife of tongues, with which for his maſters ſake he had a continual conflict untill he overcame by the blood of the Lamb and the word of his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, not loving his life unto the death, by which alſo he ſealed this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Teſtimony) with the conſent of others concurring, thought it expedient to ſlip no time, but take the firſt &amp; the fitteſt opportunity of ſpreading it among them in ſuch away as might be leaſt offencive. And accordingly, haſtening to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the time of his appoynted diſſolution, a litle before his being taken, he delivered it upon the 17. day of Januarii as it were his dying Teſtimony into the hands of a Reverend &amp; learned Miniſter, whom he ſuppoſed to be the Moderator of the meeting at <hi>Edinburgh:</hi> who, not knowing him (for if he had, its like his knoun Loyaltie, and reſpect to the Councils ſentence of Intercommuning, would have made him more reſerved; as he shewed himſelf afterward, when one of the <hi>Informatorie Vindications,</hi> was offered to him, which he ſuperciliouſly refuſed) at that time, recieved it very courteouſly, and promiſed to conſider &amp; communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it to his Brethren. Which for ſome time was expected, in the hope that either he or ſome other, should have had ſo much regard to the importance of the matter of it about which it treats, or reſpect to him, who ſet to his dying ſeal to it, or tenderneſs to our Souls, who adhere to it if they think us in an error, or Zeal for the Covenanted Cauſe, if they think that thereby wronged, as to ſignify their ſentiments of it, in approving what is right, and diſapproving what is wrong in it. Yet in ſtead of this, after it hath been much ſpoken of and inquired after, by occaſion of its being confirmed by a Martyrs Teſtimony, it hath been not only ſmothered and imbezilled, but when ſought for, repreſented as inſignificant, impertinent non-ſenſe, not worthie of their Cognizance. Which indeed is the eaſieſt way, and shorteſt cutt to anſwer all things: And perhaps it were not worth the while, to vindicate the weakneſs of ſome of our hands in it from ſome ſuch Charge. But ſuppoſe it were, the matter of it (thô weakly managed) is of ſome conſideration. It is a Teſtimony
<pb facs="tcp:45791:3"/>againſt the Addreſſers for, Accepters of, and all that have any intereſt in, or acceſſion to this <hi>Toleration;</hi> with reflections upon the Granters deſign, and the Receivers ſin: Surely if they have Loyalty for the Granter, and love to the benefite Granted, and peace in improving it, they muſt Juſtify it; and how ever it is incumbent to watchmen to shew whether it be ſin or duty to theſe that challenge and Alledge it to be ſin. It is a Teſtimony for the <hi>Covenants,</hi> now interdicted to be ouned; which all Presbyterians muſt Avouch, or elſe their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence thereunto will be ſuſpected. It is a Teſtimony for the preſent expediency of <hi>Field meetings,</hi> not long agoe Generaly approven of Presbyterian Miniſters, &amp; even of them who now condemn them in the ſame Circumſtances, wherein they themſelves maintained them; It is worthie of ſome Cognizance either to purge themſelves of unſtedfaſtneſs, or impute to them folly who charge it, and to tell whether it be ſin or duty, when People are daylie brought to ſuffering upon this head. What if it have no ſignificancy, hath it no ſignification? Or cannot theſe Maſters of ſenſe &amp; learning underſtand the ſcope of that which Conſcience ſpeaks, &amp; it concerns theirs to hear, thô it do not obſerve the rules of Grammer: What if it be folly? Yet they knew not, but the Caſe may be ſuch as makes the anſwer expedient, <hi>leſt we be wiſe in our oun conceit,</hi> when they do not diſcover our folly: Or shall we allow our ſelves to think, they care not what conceits or deceits we run upon? But we rather conjecture, the other caſe of Anſwering folly, that the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man determines in the negative, doth more bind our Brethren, that is, they will not anſwer, <hi>leſt they be like unto us:</hi> for either they may fear to diſcover ſome folly too, &amp; then they will be like unto us; or elſe, by breaking ſilence, and the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries preſcribed in the Terms wherein they are Tolerated, they may break the Toleration, loſs their patrons protection, and then they will be like unto us. And there is ſome reaſon to think this Policy preponderates with them, which indeed as thy are Circumſtantiated may conciliate pity: For, if they anſwer, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcovering the Conſtantly aſſerted principls of Presbyterians, concerning Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of or from Papiſts, &amp; ouning the Obligation of the Covenants, &amp;c. All will ſuſpect them either of prevarication or palpable defection; If they do diſcover them, they will forfeit the fancied benefite of the pretended favour. But we would have them alſo to conſider, that if they be altogether ſilent at ſuch a time, thô their known learning and ſenſe will abſolve them from inability to anſwer it, yet their diſdain of our ignorance, will not clear them of the Cenſure of unfaithfulneſs. And let not their fear of Papiſts &amp; Malignants, if they do ſpeak, make them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together miſregard our conſtantly reſolved Teſtifying againſt them, if they do not ſpeak, inſignificant &amp; impertinent as it is. However the preſent induſtry to cover &amp; ſmother it, together with the inconvenience of incorrect Copies, &amp; the mocks &amp; jears, wherwith they are intertained, do provoke us to make it more publick, &amp; to take this way of publishing it; that impartial unprejudiced Readers, may ſee with their oun eyes, &amp; at leaſt be invited &amp; incited to ſearch &amp; try, whether the courſe here teſtified againſt, be to be approved or reproved, &amp; conſequently whether to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced or diſcountenanced: And what light they obtain by ſearching the Scriptures, whether theſe things be ſo, it is deſired they may aſcribe all the praiſe of it, to the Father of Lights, &amp; not aſtrict all the profit of it to their oun breaſts, but impart it alſo to others; &amp; not with hold it from thoſe, who oune this Teſtimony, who deſire nothing more than to be friendly admonished of any wrong in their way, that being convinced thereof, they may confeſs &amp; forſake it, and to do to others whatſoever thy would that men should do to them. Fare wel.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45791:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE TESTIMONY, OF</hi> Some perſecuted Presbyterian Ministers of the Goſpel, unto the Reformation of the Church of Scotland, namely to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual obligation of the National Covenant, and ſolemn League and Covenant, and to the preſent expediencie of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing to preach the Goſpel in the interdicted Meetings in the Fields : And againſt this Antichriſtian Toleration, in its nature and deſign, tending to bury all theſe in oblivion, lately obtruded upon, and accepted by the body of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; given in to the Miniſters at Edenburgh, by <hi>Mr. James Renwick. 17.</hi> Jan. <hi>1688.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was ever reckoned the renown of the Church of Scotland, thô now brought very low, and like to be loſt as a prey in the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons mouth, that Chriſts conqueſt of that Land which the Roman Legions while heathenish could not ſubdue, among the firſt fruits of the Gentiles. And when overcome and long overrun by Roman Locuſts when Antichriſtian, his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious outſtretched Arm did emancipate and redeem his Inheritance from the bondage of Antichriſt unto ſuch a Pitch of Reformation in Doctrine, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, Diſcipline and Government, that it becam a Pattern to other Churches, and had this prerogative above them all, that at once and from the begining, nothing was left unremoved or unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that ever flowed from the man of ſin: And every part of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was regulated by the meaſuring line of the Sanctuary, the Word of God; And not only eſtablished by righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and laudable Laws ratifying the ſame with the Sanction of the penal Statuts againſt the enemies thereof, but confirmed with ſtricteſt Engagements to preſerve and promote it, in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and ſolemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, whereby Scotland became the Inheritance of the Prince of the Kings of the Earth by manifold and undoubted Rights, by his Fathers Grant, by his oun Purchaſe; and by our ſolemn Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; Dedition by Covenant: Whereof ever ſince he took Infeftment, he hath continued his poſſeſſion, and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Title by the Teſtimonies of his Witneſſes againſt all Invaſions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, through all the periods of this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45791:4"/>Church which alſo hath ever been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the Glory of this Reformed and Covenanted Church, that nothing was ever attempted againſt any part of her Reformation, but was faithfully wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed againſt by Miniſters and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, from time to time: Eſpecially from its firſt eſtablishment, and aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Popery, no eſſay could ever be made to introduce, or procure the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of any of its ſuperſtitious fop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries, but the Zeal of the Lords wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes was found to flame againſt it, with a pecularity of fervor. It was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver known in Scotland, before this laſt fatal Degeneration that ever a favour could be obtained to Papiſts to practiſe their Idolatries, without a reſolute Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation againſt it, much leſs was it ever heard that the open Profeſſion of it, should not only be allowed without control, but applauded in the congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulatory Addreſſes of ſome called Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and Presbyterians, for a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration Declaredly Deſigned to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it. The Addreſſes of Proteſtants on ſuch an occaſion uſed to run in an other ſtrain. There is one dated Maij 27. 1561. preſented to the Council. <q>Shewing that honeſty craved them, and Conſcience moved them to make the ſecrets of their hearts patent, which was, that before ever theſe Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants and Dumb Dogs empire over them, they were fully determined to hazard life, and whatſoever they had received of God in temporal things: And that theſe enemies of God might aſſure themſelves, that if the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil put not order to them they should shortly take ſuch order that they shall neither be able to do what they liſt, neither yet live upon the ſweat of the browes of ſuch as are no debtors to them.</q> Nor were ever wanting in their warnings and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings againſt the leaſt remiſsneſs in Zeal againſt Papiſts, or any tendencie towards favouring them: As when the miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Mary the Daughter of the degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Queen returning from France, ſet up the Maſs but in her oun family, the Godly at that time gave plain ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they could not abide, that the Land which God by his power had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from Idolatry should in their eyes be polluted again, and that Idol be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered again to take place in this Realm. And a Proclamation being then emit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to protect the Queens Domeſtick Servants that were Papiſts, there was not wanting a peremptoty Proteſtation againſt it. That if any of her Servants shall commit idolatry, ſay Maſs, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate therewith or take the defence thereof, in that caſe this Proclaimation should not be extended to them, nor be a ſafeguard to them in that behalf, no more than if they commit murder. But that it may be lawful to inflict upon them the pains contained in Gods Word againſt Idolaters, wherever they might be apprehended without favour. Mr. Knox had ſuch an impreſſion of the danger of ſuch a Toleration that he counted it a Joyning hands with Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. And declared that one Maſs was more fearful to him, than if ten thouſand armed Enemies were Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of purpoſe to ſuppreſs the whole Religion, for, ſaid he, in our God there is ſtrength to reſiſt and confound Multitudes, if we unfeignedly depend upon him; But when we joyne hands with Idolatry, it is no doubt, but both Gods amiable preſence, and comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able defence will leave us, and what shall then become of us? Therefore in the reign of <hi>K. James</hi> VI. upon the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Plots of the Popish Lords conſpiring with the King of Spain, who yet favoured by the Kings Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, it was reſolutely declared by <hi>Mr. Davidſon</hi> that it favoured much of defection in thoſe dayes, that ſuch no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Rebells to God, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45791:5"/>should be ſo treated with; and that a door should not be opened to Gods enemies. And when a Convention in Falkland was conſulting to call home theſe conſpiring Traitors, <hi>Mr. Andrew Melvin</hi> thought it his duty to go thither uncalled, and when rebuked by the King for his boldneſs, took the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to charge him and the Eſtates in the Name of Chriſt and his Church, not to favour Chriſts Enemies whom he hateth, nor go about to make Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of theſe who have traterouſly ſought to betray their City and Native Country, with the overthrow of Chriſts Kingdom. And to challenge them with Treaſon againſt Chriſt, his Church, and the Country in that purpoſe they were about. Afterwards when the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted Reformation was upon the aſcendant and meeting with multifarous aſſaults from all hands, how impartial and uniforme the witneſs of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful was againſt the Toleration of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious errors, the warnings &amp; Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the General Aſſemblies do evidence beyond contradiction. And after the invaſion of the Sectaries, the Teſtimony of ſundry Miniſters of the Goſpel in the Provinces of Perth and Fife againſt their vaſt Toleration is yet in the hands, and recent in the hearts of theſe that deſire to retain former principles: Beſides the many writtings of Truths Champions againſt it, which are yet on record. This hath been the conſtant tenor of the Teſtimonies of the witneſſes of Chriſt, ever before this woful &amp; wretched Cataſtrophe, which puts an indelible infamy on the sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſecuritie, &amp; aſs-like ſtupiditie of this generation; That having received ſuch an excellent Teſtimony, depoſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed &amp; transmitted to us through a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued tract of witneſſings &amp; wreſtlings of our worthy Anceſtors, now to let it ſlip &amp; ſlide through our feeble fingers. Whereby as we have forfeited the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of being eſteemed the off-ſpring of ſuch Heroes (while we not only ſuffer &amp; conſent to, but congratulate &amp; applaude the Introduction &amp; Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment, at leaſt do embrace &amp; cloſe with that which is introductive of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry &amp; Tyrannie, Poperie &amp; the Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, they built with ſo great expenſe) ſo we may fear the curſe of poſterity for interrupting the propagation of ſo excellent a Teſtimony to ſucceeding generations, who when they shall read the flattering &amp; fauning Addreſſes of this age to, &amp; of their ſo haſty &amp; hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry embracements of enſnaring &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive favours, from an Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Tyrant, ſo palpably deſigned for, &amp; ſo properly &amp; natively tending to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the undermining &amp; overturning of the Reformation, will diſdain &amp; diſoune ſuch for their Fathers, with indignation at their memory, for ſuch dishonourable &amp; daſtardly yeeldings. <hi>O let it not be told in Goth, nor published in the ſtreets of Aſskelon,</hi> that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are ſo far degenerate. Alas all that hear of it will hiſs at them for this, that as they had been ſilent &amp; omitted a ſeaſonable, Teſtimony againſt abjured Prelacy, &amp; blasphemous Supremacy, when theſe were introduced; So now alſo even when this Myſterie &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy of Popery &amp; Tyranny twiſted together in the preſent deſign of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, had made ſo great a progreſs, &amp; was evidently brought above bourd: So except what was endeavoured in a Proteſtation emitted at Sanquhair Maij 28. 1685. (Which here we homelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate) the Generality were left to forego this opportunity of a Teſtimony alſo, to the reproach, of the ſometimes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Church of Scotland. Yea the very rabble may ariſe in Judgement againſt them in that they teſtified their deteſtation of the firſt erection of the Idolatrous Maſs; &amp; ſome of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery, and ſuch as had no Profeſſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45791:5"/>of Religion, ſuffered unto death for ſpeaking againſt Popery, &amp; the deſign of the King, while the Miniſters were ſilent: And ſome of the Curats, &amp; Members of the late Parliament, made ſome ſtickling againſt Papiſts, while Presbyterians, from whom might have been expected greater oppoſition, were ſleeping in a profound ſubmiſſion. Wherefore thô we be very inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant nothings, &amp; therefore both inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable &amp; unworthy to aim at ſupplying this vacancy of a Teſtimony, &amp; dare not aſpire unto the preſumption of think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fulfill it, with any proportion to the moment &amp; merit or the matter of this clamant Caſe of Confeſſion; Yet conſidering the weight &amp; worth, profite, &amp; price of thoſe Truths, now committed to us to Teſtifie &amp; ſuffer for, our indiſputable duty as Miniſters &amp; Members of this Church; The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible obligation of our Holy Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants; The eminent dangers immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent on the Land, apparently ineluct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, if not prevented by giving &amp; tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing timeous warning: We cannot, muſt not, dare not forbear to offer our Mite of a Teſtimony, for the preſent precious Word of our Lords patience, and the Covenanted Reformation of Scotland, in Doctrine, Worship, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, &amp; Government; &amp; againſt all the Injuries, inſolent Indignities, &amp; audacious encroachments, done unto, &amp; made upon the ſame, by which God is highly dishonoured, the Throne of his Glory affronted, the Kingdom of his Son undermined, &amp; many Souls dreadfully involved in the guilt of this Confederacy againſt him. And ſo much the more confidence we have, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity we find, to prompt to this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, that both this duty is aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned by others, &amp; impoſed upon us by reaſon of the ſtill continuing and growing perſecution inceſſantly purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, without relenting, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding others are flattered with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of clemency, &amp; tenderneſs to Conſcience, which is both encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; engaging to us to maintain this Teſtimony for which we ſuffer, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſequeſtred from others, &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate (we ſay, not from the benefite, but) from the ſnare &amp; curſe of this Toleration by the late Proclamations againſt us, we take the more boldneſs, &amp; have the more advantage to ſpeak our minds, that what we ſay, as it is not by communication with others, ſo it cannot endanger any but our ſelves. And for what danger, we may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to upon this ſo honourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, We are not careful in this matter: Our God is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace, &amp; if not, we think it rather a matter ſo be ambitious of, than of shame or fear, to be endangered there upon.</p>
            <p>The preſent Invader of the Regal power, in his Proclamation of the Twentieth of Feberwarii laſt paſt 1687. hath by his Sovereign Authority, prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Royal, &amp; abſolute power, which he requires all his Subjects to obey with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſerve, granted a Toleration to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, to Quakers, &amp; to Moderate Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, under certain conditions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictions &amp; Limitations. In Which Proclamation the Moderate Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians are Tolerate only to meet in their private houſes &amp; only to hear ſuch Miniſters as accept of this Indulgence, &amp; none other (whereby all adhering to old Presbyterian principles &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations againſt ſuch a vaſt Toleration are excluded, &amp; ſuch admitted to be heard who have receded from them) who are thereby obliged to ſay or do nothing contrary to the peace of his reign, ſeditious, or treaſonable, under the higheſt pains theſe crimes will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, (&amp; conſequently muſt not declare that part of the Counſel of God, which cencerns his Antichriſtian enemies but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45791:6"/>conſent that faithfulneſs to Chriſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a Crime) nor are they to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to build Meeting-houſes, or to uſe out-houſes or barnes (but content themſelves with the confinements, whereunto, they are reſtricted in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel) In the mean time all Preachers, Aſſiſters &amp; Connivers at Field Meetings are to be perſecuted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the utmoſt ſeverity of the Laws made againſt them. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs all Laws or Acts of Parliament, Cuſtoms or Conſtitutions, made or executed againſt any of the Popish way, are ſuſpended ſtoped &amp; diſabled (and conſequently all the Legal Eſtablish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Proteſtant Religion are unhinged) ſo that they shall be in all reſpects as free, as any Proteſtants whatſoever, not only to exerciſe their Religion, but to enjoy all Offices, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, &amp;c. Which he shall think fit to beſtow upon them in all time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (whereby he may put in any Popish Prieſt, in any Paroch Church, when he pleaſes) wherein alſo he claims a power of vacuating &amp; annulling heritable rights (&amp; by that ſame power may invade mens heretable properties, when he is pleaſed ſo to exert his Abſolutneſs) &amp; of caſſing &amp; diſcharging all former Oaths: And in place of all, ſubſtituting a new one, wherein he requires all his ſubjects or ſuch of them, as he or his Council shall pleaſe, to ſwear that they acknowledge him to be rightful King &amp; Supreme Governour of the three Realms, &amp; over all Perſons therein. (Not over all Cauſes, for the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Supremacy is reſtored to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt from whom it was borrowed, &amp; for which there is no uſe at preſent, Abſolute power may do the turn as well as this) that they hold it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for ſubjects on any pretence, or for any cauſe whatſoever (even thô he should command his Popish Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries to maſſacre all Proteſtants, which is the tender mercy &amp; burning fervent charity of Papiſts) to riſe in armes againſt him, &amp; that they shall never practiſe, or aſſiſt the Practiſers of the ſame; &amp; that they shall never reſiſt his power, nor oppoſe his Authority to his perſon (which is the Compend of all the former Oaths, &amp; further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends an Engagement to juſtify all his perſonal Adminiſtrations, thô never ſo outragious as Acts of Lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority) but upon the other hand shall to the utmoſt of their power, defend &amp; maintain him his heirs &amp; Succeſſors, in the exerciſe of their abſolute power &amp; Authority againſt all deadly (where they are to engage not only to oune his power, paramouut &amp; tranſcendent to all Law divine &amp; humane, &amp; to mancipate their Religion &amp; reaſon with all their Religious &amp; civil Liberties, to the Luſtful rage, &amp; unbridled will of a Tyrant; But if he should erect the formal &amp; direct worship of Devils, &amp; bring all their necks under the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring, they muſt neither reſiſt it, nor contradict it, but upon the other hand actively concur with him, in doing all his will to the greateſt exceſs of ryot, And muſt become executioners of their Fathers Mothers, Wives &amp; Children, if it shall pleaſe him to put forth his abſolute power in that exerciſe; For herein he claims &amp; hereby is given a power to command what he will, &amp; obliging Subjects to obey whatſoever he will command, to obey abſolutely without reſerve, without reſerve of Conſcience, Religion, Honour, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, or Reaſon: Which proclaims him in whoſe name the Proclamation is emitted, the greateſt Tyrant that ever lived in the World, far ſurmounting all the luſt, impudence, &amp; inſolence of any Roman, Sicilian, Turkish, Tartarian, or Indian Tyrant, that ever trampled upon the Liberties of mankind.</p>
            <p>But finding this Proclamation was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45791:6"/>not well approven, becauſe of the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, odiouſneſs of this Oath; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to mend the matter in a Letter to the Council (dated March 31. 1687. the ſupreme Law at preſent) he grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to all that should deſire on theſe terms, the benefit of the ſaid Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, without being obliged to take the Oath, during his pleaſure only, or ſo long as the Council should find them behave themſelves regularly and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably without giving cauſe of offence to him, or any in Authority or truſt under him. By which none of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer reſtrictions are taken away (the Oath only excepted) but further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, that they shall not only ſay or do nothing, contrary to the peace of his reign, ſeditious or treaſonable, but that they behave themſelves regularly &amp; peaceably, without giving any cauſe of offence to him, which comprehends leſſer offences than ſedition or Treaſon, even every thing that will diſpleaſe a Tyrant, &amp; a Papiſt, that is all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in ſeaſonable duties or Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. But taking to his conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſome may eaſily put ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations upon his foreſaid Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, as may diſcover his drift &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; And, leſt his different procedure in this project with England &amp; Scotland should make his pretences to conſcience ſuſpect of Treachery, Therefore he hath fallen upon a more plauſible way &amp; given forth a more ſmooth Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, of the date the Twentieth eight of June the ſame year, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed upon the former, in which are further explications, but no taking off of former reſtrictions (except the Oath) ſeeing he further declares, that by the ſame Soveraign Authority, Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Royal &amp; abſolute power he ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends ſtops &amp; diſables all penal Laws. And to the end that by the Liberty thereby granted, the peace &amp; ſecurity of his Government in the practice there of, may not be endangered (that is, that his Tyranny may be ſecured in the peaceable Poſſeſſion of all his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments upon our Religion, Laws &amp; Liberties, in the practice of this To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration) he gives his ſubjects leave to meet &amp; ſerve God after their oun way &amp; manner (every way which is their oun, &amp; according to their model, if it be not in Chriſts way) in private Houſes, Chappels, or hired places, ſo that they take care that nothing be preached or taught, which may any way tend to alienate the hearts of the People from him or his Government (&amp; conſequently no faithful warning muſt be given of the ſins, duties or dangers of theſe times, or Teſtimony againſt the wickedneſs of this Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or the wickedneſs of the Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, by any that accept it, for theſe would be interpreted to have a tendency to alienate from the Government) &amp; that their Meetings be peaceably held (ſuitably to this commenced confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy with Antichriſt who here requires of all, who take the benefite of the preſent truce with him, &amp; binding to the good behaviour) &amp; publickly all perſons freely admitted to them, (which is for the Informing trade, that Jeſuites flies, may have acceſs to obſerve and delate how the Inſtructions are kept) &amp; that they ſignify to ſome of the next privie Councillors Sherifs, &amp;c. What places are ſet a part for the uſes, with the names of the Preachers (whereby they are reſtricted to the terms of a formal bargain, &amp; muſt have their leaſe &amp; licence for every place of preaching, &amp; no perſons are admitted, but ſuch as give up their names excluding here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all that for any meaſure of faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in duty are obnoxious to their wicked Laws) in the mean time Field Meetings are ſtrictly prohibited, &amp; all Laws &amp; Acts of Parliament are left in full force &amp; vigor againſt them; for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45791:7"/>which now he ſayes after this favour, ſurpaſſing the hopes, &amp; equalling the very wishes of the moſt Zealouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, there is no shadow of excuſe left (which may hold to true of ſome, who by this acceptance diſcover their hopes &amp; wishes, &amp; Zeal to be termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate upon peace rather than Truth, eaſe rather than duty, &amp; their oun things rather than the things of Chriſt: But as for us, it ſome way answers our fears, &amp; correſponds with our jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies; And therefore while others are rejoycing under the shadow of ſuch a bramble, we think it matter of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not becauſe we are excluded from the benefite of it, but that ſo many are included in the guilt of it, &amp; expoſed to the curſe of it; And do look upon it, as a ſeaſonable &amp; neceſſary Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for the Cauſe of Chriſt, &amp; the Intereſt of the Proteſtant Religion, &amp; the Laws &amp; Liberties of the Country, all overturned &amp; ſubverted by this To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, to keep our Meetings as in former times in the open Fields, whether his Tyranny hath driven us.</p>
            <p>But theſe who are carrying on wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed deſigns know not what courſe to take as moſt effectual for gaining their ends, &amp; do change their methods ſo oft as they change their thoughts about the means moſt apparently ſucceſsful: So he hath again thought fit to give out another Proclamation of the date the fifth day of October, the foreſaid year, declaring not only that all perſons, Preachers &amp; hearers that are preſent at any Meeting in the open Fields (which are their greateſt eyeſore, becauſe the Rights of the Crown &amp; Kingdom of Chriſt are there pleaded, aſſerted &amp; vindicated) but alſo all diſſenting Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, who shall take upon them to preach in houſes, without obſerving the foreſaid directions, as are preſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the late Proclamation, viz. (that nothing be preached or taught among them, which may any way tend to alienate the hearts of the People from this abſolute &amp; incontrollable Monarch or his Government, &amp; that their Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings be peaceably, openly, &amp; publickly held, &amp; all perſons freely admitted to them; And that they do ſignify and make known to ſome one or moe of his privie Councillors, Sheriffs, Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warts, Bailies, Juſtices of peace, or Magiſtrates of Royal Burrowghs, what place or places they ſet apart for theſe uſes, with the names of the Preachers) shall be alſo proſecuted with the utmoſt rigor &amp; ſeverity, that their Laws will allow. And to make all ſure, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth every one of his foreſaid Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, to whom ſuch intimation shall be made, to ſend to the Clerks of the privie Council once every moneth, the names &amp; Sirnames of the Preachers, &amp; the times &amp; places of their Meetings. In all this unexpected Clemency (as he terms it) not ſatisfying himſelf with what he hath declared againſt Field Meetings, in the forſaid Proclamations concerning them, he giveth out yet another of the date the 18. of October laſt againſt ſuch Meetings, calling ſuch aſſemblies for the Worship of God, Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouzes of Rebellion, Authorizing all Officers, Civil &amp; Military to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, ſecure in firmance the perſons of ſome Miniſters, &amp; for encouragment, enſures them the ſumm of 100. p. Sterl. for each of theſe Miniſters; A goodly price, where with not only they, but their Maſter &amp; Meſſage are prized, &amp; put upon ſome, who ever ſince the firſt of theſe Proclamations have been ſo unhappy as to be innocent of theſe things laid to their charge, being out of the Kingdom, &amp; ſo out of capacity to concur in that duty of carrying and following Chriſts ſtandart in the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Goſpel, indiſpenſibly required of all his Confeſſors that are in it. Which as it proclaims the manifeſt impudence
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45791:7"/>of thoſe lies, wherewith the Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſtuffed; So it may provoke all who are touched with zeal againſt the Indignities done to Chriſt, &amp; would be accounted among his faithful witneſſes, againſt the preſent Antichriſtian deſign, to an ambition of expoſing themſelves to the reproach of ſuch lying mouths, the greateſt honour of the Servants of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Having now in this delineation of the foreſaid Proclamations already diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered ſomewhat of the obvious ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the preſent deſign againſt our Covenanted Reformation: We shall now proceed to offer our Teſtimony for the ſame, againſt the preſent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to ruine &amp; zaze it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the firſt place, Teſtifie againſt the Toleration; And next for the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of our Covenants, &amp; the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity &amp; expediency of keeping our Meetings in the Fields, the ſuppreſſion of which being one of the wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the Toleration, that ſuſpends other Laws, but leaves all in force &amp; vigor againſt theſe.</p>
            <p>But ere we begin with the firſt of theſe, that we may clear the matter, prevent miſtakes, &amp; preoccupy objections, we muſt premit. 1. That Lawful Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats are placed in the Common-wealth by God, the Supreme Governour of the whole World, to be a terror to evildoers, &amp; a praiſe to them that do well; So they rule not for men, but for God, with whom is no iniquity: But as Tyrants &amp; Uſurpers have no more intereſt in this than Robbers have in the Authorization of rightful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties; So where Magiſtrats are Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, &amp; acting Lawfully, they will find it their duty to be a terror to theſe evil doers, who are now Tolerated, &amp; a praiſe to them, who are perſecuted. 2. We cheerfully ſubſcribe to that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of our Confeſſion of Faith <hi>Chap.</hi> 23. § 4. That Infidelity or difference in Religion doth not make void the Magiſtrats juſt &amp; legal Authority, nor free the People from the due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to him. But we think it no way inconſiſtent therewith to ſay with <hi>Naphthali</hi> pag. 6. <hi>Prior Edit.</hi> Let the words be conſidered, &amp; we are confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that no ſober man will think the acknowledgment of juſt &amp; legal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, &amp; due obedience a rational ground to infer that Tyranny is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by either allowed or priviledged. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we grant all that is in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, viz. <hi>Dominium non fundari in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratia.</hi> Yet this we aſſert; that a Prince, who not only is of another Religion, but an avowed enemy to, &amp; overturner of the Religion eſtablished by Law, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending &amp; endeavouring to introduce a heretical, falſe, Blaſphemous &amp; Idolat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Religion, can claim no juſt &amp; legal Authority; but in this caſe, the People may very lawfully decline his pretended uſurped Authority. For thô Infidelity or difference of Religion, does not make void Authority, where it is lawfully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with conſent of the People, &amp; without encroachment on their religious &amp; legal Liberties; Yet it may incapacitate a perſon, &amp; lawfully ſeclude him from Authority, over a Chriſtian People having the reformed Religion eſtablish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Law, &amp; confirmed by ſolemn &amp; national Covenants, both according to the Laws of the Land, which do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacite a Papiſt of all Authority, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme or Subordinate; And by the Oath of Coronation, which obliges all Kings at the reception of their Princely Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to make their faithful promiſe to maintain the true Religion of Chriſt Jeſus (by which ever ſince the framing of that Oath, was meant only the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion) &amp; shall abolish and gainſtand all falſe Religions, &amp;c. And conſequently muſt not ſo much as To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate Popery which no Papiſts can engage, or be admitted to ſwear, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45791:8"/>to the Word of God, which forbids expreſsly to ſet a Stranger over us, who is not our Brother <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.15. Which includes as wel a ſtranger of a ſtrange Religion, as one of a ſtrange Country. This is not our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only; It is aſſerted by Doctor <hi>Guild</hi> in his expoſition 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.1, 2. Obſerve 5 <hi>pag.</hi> 104. We infer the general rule of election of Magiſtrats, as well in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his qualities, &amp; form of election as of the end, wherefore he is to be elected. As for his qualities 1 He muſt not be a ſtranger in birth, much leſs in Religion, but muſt be of a conjunction natural &amp; ſpiritual with them whom he governeth, otherwiſe there can be no ſympathie nor ſymbolizing between them. 2. He muſt be able to govern, which is called here to lead out &amp; in: Next the form of his election should be by common &amp; voluntary conſent, according to the conſtitution of the State, &amp; Oath or obligation of right adminiſtration, the rule whereof, should be the Law of God, &amp; poſitive Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the realm, and laſt the end should be to feed the People, caring that they be ſpiritually fed in the food of life, &amp; temporally, that they be not ſpoyled, or bereft of their means of the life corporal, to be their Guider, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, Father, Patron, &amp; to have a regard to all neceſſities, as the good Paſtor hath to his sheep &amp; the Father to his family. And before him, it is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Famous <hi>Mr. Knox,</hi> whoſe four propoſitions, as they are to be read, in the account of his life, before his Hiſtory in quarto, &amp; proſecuted in his ſecond blaſt, we shall here inſert. 1. It is not birth only, nor propinquity of blood that maketh a King lawfully to reign, over a People Profeſſing Chriſt Jeſus, &amp; his Eternal verity, but in his election, the ordinance, which God hath eſtablished in the election of inferiour Judges muſt be obſerved. 2. No ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Idolater, nor notorious transgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of Gods Holy precepts, ought to be promoted to any publick Regiment, honour or dignity, in any realm, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince or City, that hath ſubjected them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Chriſt Jeſus, &amp; his bleſſed Evangel. 3. Neither can Oath or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe bind any ſuch People, to obey &amp; maintain Tyrants againſt God, &amp; his Truth known. 4. But if rashly they have promoted any manifeſt wicked perſon, or yet ignorantly have choſen ſuch an one, as after declareth himſelf unworthy of regiment above the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God (&amp; ſuch be all Idola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> &amp; cruel perſecuters) moſt juſtly may the ſame men depoſe &amp; punish him, that unadviſedly before they did nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, appoint &amp; elect. And beſides we are to remember, the practice of theſe venerable divines, that penned that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Confeſſion, how avowedly they profeſſed &amp; proſecuted, &amp; ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated &amp; encouraged the Parliament to an oppoſition to the then King, abuſing his Authority to the detriment of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion &amp; Liberty, &amp; to the obſtruction of Reformation: And the declared prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the general aſſembly of this Church, when they refuſed to concur in that unlawful engagement, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt till ſecurity were had by ſolemn Oath under his hand &amp; ſeal. That he should for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf &amp; Succeſſors, give his Aſſent to all Acts &amp; Bills, for enjoyning Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Government, &amp; never make op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to it, nor endeavour, any change thereof July ult. 1648. ſeſs. 21. And when they refuſed to admit <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> the ſecond to the exerciſe of his power, except he should take the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, as it is to be ſeen in their ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable &amp; neceſſary warning July 27. ſeſs. 27. 1649. And in the Act of the Weſt Kirk Auguſt 13. 1650. wherein they declare that they will not oune him nor his Intereſt, otherwayes than
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45791:8"/>with a ſubordination to God, &amp; ſo far as he ounes &amp; proſecutes the Cauſe of God &amp; diſclaims his &amp; his Fathers op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Work of God, &amp; to the Covenant. By all theſe it is evident, that our renowned Reformers, were not men of ſuch a principle, as that People were bound to oune, obey, &amp; maintain a Tyrant againſt God, &amp; his Truth: And that neither the Authors of our Confeſſion of Faith in England, nor owners thereof in Scotland, did ever underſtand that Article ſo, as that a Malignant enemy to our Covenanted Reformation, let be an Idolaterous he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical Enemy to the Chriſtian Religion, could be capable of bearing rule, or owned to be a Ruler over the Lords People in Britain &amp; Ireland: And that could ground the intire Loyaltie ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed upon it by the Citizens &amp; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of Edinburgh &amp; Cannongate, that give out themſelves to be of the Presbyterian perſuaſion, &amp; profeſſed by them in their Addreſs to the perſon &amp; Government of ſuch an one, as the Duke of York. 3. It is the right and duty of Magiſtrats to uſe an impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, coercive &amp; cumulative power about Church matters, in commanding Miniſters to do their miniſterial du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, preſcribed unto them, by their only Head &amp; Maſter Chriſt; In reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Idolatry, Superſtition, error and Prophanneſs; In giving the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of Chriſt their protection, and adde their civil ſanction to juſt &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eceleſiaſtick decrees. And it is the duty of Miniſters, to grant unto the Magiſtrate all the foreſaid power, and to be thankful to God, &amp; grateful to them, for the benefite of the right exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of it. And to pray for them, that we may lead a quiet &amp; peaceable life in all Godlineſs &amp; honeſty. But for uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to aſſume to themſelves a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Authority, prerogative Royal and abſolute power, to ranverſe their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, Tolerate Idolatry, &amp; allow Meetings for Goſpel Ordinances only with reſtrictions to perſons who may preach, places where they may preach, &amp; matter what they shall preach, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be allowed by any, who dare not have a hand in betraying the Church &amp; yeelding to all ſuch encroachments on her Liberties: And to pray for the proſperity of Tyrants, that we may be enſlaved in our Religion &amp; Liberty, is a wicked thing. 4. It is indeed the hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of Kings &amp; happineſs of People, to have true Humane &amp; Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, eſtablished in the common wealth, that is, Liberty of perſons from ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Liberty of priviledges from Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp; Liberty of Conſcience from all Impoſitions of men, conſiſting in a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from the Doctrines, Traditions or the Commandments of men, againſt or beſide the Word of God, in the free enjoyment of Goſpel Ordinances in purity &amp; power, &amp; in the free obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance &amp; eſtablishment of all his Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of Doctrine, Worship, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline &amp; Government, in ſubordination to the only rule conſcience, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed will of its only Lawgiver Jeſus Chriſt. When this is ratified as a right, by the Sanction of approven Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp; countenanced &amp; encouraged as Religion, by the confirmation of Laws, approving whatſoever is commanded by the God of Heaven, to be done for the Houſe of the God of Heaven (which is the full amount of all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats Authority) then we are obliged to accept of it, with all thankful ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation: But ſuch a Liberty, as over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns our Rights, our Priviledges, our Religion, &amp; Tolerats it only under the notion of a crime, &amp; Indemnifes it under the notion of a fault to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, &amp; allowes the exerciſe thereof only in part, ſo &amp; ſo modified, cannot be accepted by any to whom the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach thereof is a burden, &amp; to whom
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45791:9"/>the reproaches of Chriſt, are in eſteem, in ſuch a day, when even the hoofs of Chriſts Intereſt, buried in bondage, are to be contended for. What Liberty this may be to ſome Conſciences. It is none to the tender, according to the rule of Conſcience. 5. It is certain a Magiſtrate ought to reſtore, what right or Liberty, he hath robbed from the Church, if it be the ſame Liberty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, that was taken away. Yea we concede, if a Magiſtrate shall grant a ſimple permiſſion &amp; Liberty to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Church, to exerciſe all the parts of their Office without any encroachment upon any kind of power ſeated in Churches Indicatories, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no ſinful tendency, Miniſters may lawfully improve it, for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt: But this is ſo far from being the ſame that was taken away, that no part of it is reſtored as it was robbed, but ſo defaced &amp; depraved with Antichriſtian &amp; Tyrannical Modifications, that none that adhere to Scotlands Reformation, can receive it, as apart of that Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wherewith Chriſt had made them freer 6. As it is Miniſters duty, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their Commiſſion &amp; Charge from Chriſt, to exerciſe all the parts of their Office fully &amp; freely, whither Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats will or not; So if we might have Liberty ſo to exerciſe our function in a freedom from civil reſtraints we would willingly take &amp; improve it. Yea as we abhore the continued perſecution againſt us, not ſo much for the wrongs we ſuſtain by it, as for the wickedneſs thereof; So we deteſt the extending of it againſt any for Religion or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, or the offering violence to any mans Conſcience, &amp; in a ſafe ſenſe could allow that principle, which he would make the world believe to be his, who now ſeeks to withdraw all Conſciences from the trwe &amp; only Rule of it, that it ought not to be violented or (as it is ſaid in the English Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) <hi>forced in matters of meer Religion; or that invincible neceſſity, ought not to be uſed againſt any man on the account of his perſuaſion.</hi> If his conſtant encroachments upon our lives, Laws and Liberties, &amp; all our Intereſts as men &amp; Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, beſides the known bloody Tenets of Papiſts, did not manifeſt the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of this lying pretence, and if it were not notour, that even ſince this pretended Liberty, many have been ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, impriſoned &amp; purſued, meerly for Conſcience ſake. And it muſt be great blindneſs not to ſee, &amp; great boldneſs willingly to winck at that double faced equivocation, in matters of meer Religion, or uſing invincible neceſſity; By which he can elude when he pleaſes all theſe flattering pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of tenderneſs, by excepting at the moſt neceſſary &amp; indiſpenſible du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, if either they be ſuch, wherein any other Intereſt is concerned, beſide meer Religion or if the troubles ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained thereupon; be not altogether invincible neceſſities. Hence the plain falshood &amp; doubleneſs of his aſſertions, as to what is paſt, may give ground to conclude his intended perfidie in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of what is future. But to accept of a Liberty clogged with encroachments upon the Liberties of Chriſts free King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or either formally or interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively, directly or indirectly to give way to a Toleration of Idolatrous or falſe wayes of worship, is odious to all that know the rule of Conſcience: Thô Conſcience is not to be forced either to Religion or Irreligion; And Religion is not to be propogated by force, yet the open efforts &amp; overt-acts, &amp; propagation of Irreligion, Atheiſm, Idolatry, Blaſphemy, &amp;c. ought to be reſtrained by force, &amp; every perſon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to Conſcience conſtrained to give outward reſpect to the Lawgiver, &amp; rule of Conſcience. And what Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45791:9"/>is either intended, or does nativ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ely tend to Tolerate what is dishonour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable to God or deſtructive to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, cannot be embraced by any who are tender in keeping a Conſcience void of offence towards God &amp; man.</p>
            <p>Theſe things premitted. We come in the next place to declare our Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt the Toleration. And this we shall do, both as it is ſimply and complexely conſidered.</p>
            <p>Firſt conſidering it ſimply, we cannot but teſtify againſt it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard that it doth palpably croſs &amp; contradict the will of God, revealed in the Scriptures of Truth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.31, 32, 33. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.2-6. 25, 26. <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.6, 12. &amp;c. <hi>Josh.</hi> 22.10, 12. <hi>Josh.</hi> 23.11, 12, 13. <hi>Judg.</hi> 2.1.2, 3. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.13, 14. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.40. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.22. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.15, 16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. throughout. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.8. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.7, 8. <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.2, 3, 4. <hi>John</hi> 2.15, 16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3, 4. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.2.14, 20. <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Commiſſioners of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembly did plainly &amp; fully witneſs againſt the Toleration that was in the bud Anno 1649. And the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Aſſembly of divines at Weſt-miniſter, have in the Larger Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, in the expoſition of the ſecond Commandment, reckoned the Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of falſe Religion, amongſt the ſins forbidden therein. And in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith Chap. 20. §. 4. Aſſerted that ſuch opinions or practices as are contrary to the light of nature, or the known principles of Chriſtianity, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the external peace &amp; Order which Chriſt hath eſtablished in the Church, they may be proceeded againſt, by the Cenſures of the Church, &amp; by the power of the civil Magiſtrate. And Chap. 23. §. 3. That it is the Magiſtrats duty to take care, that the Truth of God be kept pure &amp; intire, that all blaſphemie &amp; hereſies be ſuppreſſed, all corruptions and abuſes in worship and diſcipline, prevented or reformed, &amp; all the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God, duely ſettled, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred &amp; obſerved.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In regard that a Toleration is utterly repugnant unto &amp; inconſiſtent with the indiſpenſible Oath of God in the National Covenant very expreſsly condemning it, &amp; more particularlie the ſolemn league &amp; Covenant. It is not the way to maintain (nay cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with maintaining) Reformation, to carry on a Uniformity to extirpate here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, ſuperſtition, ſchiſme, profanneſs, and whatſoever is contrary to ſound Doctrine, &amp; the power of Godlineſs; To free our Souls from the guilt of others mens ſins, to make the Lord one, &amp; his Name one; All which we are engaged &amp; ſworn unto in the preſence of Almighty God, the ſearcher of all hearts, with a true intent to performe the ſame, as we shall anſwer at the great day, when the ſecrets of all hearts shall be diſcloſed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In regard of the ſad &amp; ſinful ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, that it produceth ſuch as the growth &amp; increaſe of hereſie, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and error, the prophaning the Lords day, the contempt &amp; caſting looſe of Church diſcipline, the ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Souls, the offence of the Godly &amp; Faithful. In ſtead of Reformation, Deformation; Inſtead of the power of Godlineſs, vain Jangling; Inſtead of love, bitter heart burnings &amp; jealouſies; Inſtead of union, ſchiſme &amp; diviſon; And inſtead of peace, contention &amp; ſtrife; Inſtead of Government and Order, Anarchy &amp; Confuſion, as it is elegantly held forth &amp; evidenced by the Miniſters of Perth &amp; Fife in their forecited Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony pag. 31. The General Aſſembly of our Church in their Declaration &amp; Exhortation to their Brethren in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, ſay, what is Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but Liberty of error, ſcandal,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45791:10"/>ſchiſme, hereſie, dishonour of God, oppoſing the Truth, hindering Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, &amp; ſeducing others. And the Miniſters of the County Palatine of Lancaſter in their harmonious Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt Toleration ſubſcribed by them March. 7. 1647. do fittly adde that a Toleration is the puting a Sword into a mad mans hand, a cup of Poiſon in to the hand of a child, a letting looſe of mad men with fire brands in their hands, an appointing a city of refuge in mens Conſciences for the Devil to flee to, a laying of the ſtumbling block before the blind, a proclaiming Liberty to the Wolves to come into Chriſts fold to prey upon his Lambs; A Toleration of Soul-murther (the greateſt Murther of all other) and for the eſtablish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof damned Souls in Hell, would accurſe men on earth: Could it be to provide for tender Conſciences, to take away all Conſcience; If evil be ſuffered it will not ſuffer good; If error be not kept under, it will be Superiour. In fine, let any read <hi>Mr. Durham</hi> in his excellent Treatiſe of ſcandal, particularly part. 3. Chap. 2. pag. 146. 147. And they will ſee how he holdeth forth the Toleration, &amp; ſuffering of error to be a thing moſt hateful in its ſelf, moſt hurtful in its conſequences, &amp; moſt diſpleaſing to Chriſt: For if error, (ſaith he) be ſuch an evil, that thwarteth. 1. Both with Gods Holineſs &amp; Truth: And 2. That hazardeth ſo many Souls (for never a plague hath ſo deſtroyed the face of the viſible Church nor carried ſo many Souls to Hell as error hath done) then the ſuffering of it, cannot but be hateful to him, who Loveth his Church. 3. There is no way, whereby the Devil reproacheth Ordinances, &amp; the word, more than by this, by turning them to the quite contrary end, as if he would outshoot the Lord in his oun bow (which is abominable to mention) &amp; invert his oun means, &amp; turn his oun weapons upon him, &amp; ſuffering of this is a conniving at his deſign. 4. There is no way by which the Devil may ſo get in on Chriſts Servants to ſeduce them, as by this, as in the Epiſtle to Thyatira is clear. And can there danger come ſo nigh Chriſt &amp; he not diſpleaſed with what ſtrengtheneth their ſnares. 5. This doth equal, yea in ſome reſpect prefer the Devil to him ſo far as in us lieth, &amp; ſo cannot but provoke his jealouſie; For, ſo the Devil hath Liberty to vent his Lies with Truth equally; And there being many Lies, though there be but one Truth he hath by this moe doors opened to him than the Goſpel hath. 6. This doth make even the Truth, Ordinances and Religion it ſelf to be thought light of; When all theſe have toleration, it is on the matter a proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Indifferency to be in theſe things than which nothing can more reflect on the jealous God, who in his Word putteth ſuch a difference, &amp; sheweth ſuch deteſtation at indifferency. 7. This bringeth hudge confuſions on the Church. For 1. If theſe errors &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt teachers prevail, they carry Souls after them &amp; deſtroy them, &amp; ought that to be thought light of? 2. If they prevail not, yet they croſs, afflict &amp; offend them, &amp; ſo prove a ſnare and burden to them, of whom the Lord is tender. 8. Toleration doth either ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count litle of error, as being no hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing, &amp; ſo there can be no eſteem of Truth; or it doth account little of the deſtruction of Souls; both which muſt be abominable. 9. Error doth not only break Gods Law, but doth teach others to do ſo; &amp; ſuffering thereof muſt be a maintaining of teachers to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion &amp; Rebellion againſt the Lord.</p>
            <p>Next we witneſs againſt this preſent Toleration complexly conſidered. And that we do</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of the Granter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45791:10"/>either as to his morals, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or Relation, he is to all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering men, a perſon of that character, whoſe dainties are not to be deſired, &amp; that when he ſpeaketh is not to be believed, for there are ſeven abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations in his heart, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.25. His Plots &amp; practices in his known acceſſion to the burning of Londen 1666. In the Popish Plot diſcovered 1678. In the Murder of the Earl of Eſſex, do give ſome ſwatch and ſpecimen of his former craft &amp; cruelty, &amp; of what further he may be ſuſpected to intend as meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious to atone for ſuch villanies, to wit the Exterpation of the Proteſtant Religion, than which in the eſteem of Papiſts nothing can be more meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. And for which he hath deſerved to forefeit all truſt with men of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg or Conſcience; he is known of all to be an Excommunicat Papiſt, and a ſworn votarie &amp; vaſſal of Antichriſt, &amp; enrolled in the Societie of Jeſuites, and therefore being in his principles pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly treacherous, yea obliged to be both treacherous &amp; truculent by that Religion, he cannot be truſted in the leiſt concerns, let be thoſe of ſuch momentuous conſequence, without a ſtupid abandoning of Conſcience, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon &amp; experience; When both that known principle, <hi>that no Faith it to be kept to Hereticks,</hi> eſpouſed by all Papiſts, does to them juſtify all their lying diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations, equivocations &amp; treacheries imaginable; And that. Lateran canon, that enjoyns Kings <hi>to deſtroy &amp; extirpate Hereticks under the pain of excommunication,</hi> does oblige him to be cruel to Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, by him eſteemed to be ſuch. Beſides that in his relation, he cannot be looked upon, as a rightful or righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Magiſtrate, by any that underſtands &amp; conſiders the Inſtitution, Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, Characters &amp; Boundaries of that Sacred Ordinance, &amp; knowes by what dreadful &amp; deteſtable means he uſurped that place, who can ſay a confederacy unto, make transaction with, or take any ſecurity from ſuch a Granter, that expects the benefite of the Lords San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.12.13. If it was the Schechemites ſin &amp; shame to ſtrengthen a naughty <hi>Abimelech</hi> &amp; ſtrengthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the shadow of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.9. Much more muſt it be to take protection for Religion, as well as peace from a man of cruelty and treachery.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In reſpect of its deſign: which he himſelf expreſſeth to be to unite the hearts of his ſubjects to him in loyalty, &amp; to their Neighbours in Love: Which is to encline &amp; induce them by flatterie to lawleſs loyalty, &amp; a ſtupide con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented ſlavery, &amp; make them actively cooperate, in ſetting up, &amp; ſetling his Tyrannie in the indiſturbed poſſeſſion of all his uſurpation; And to incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate them with Babylon; For, who are the Neighbours, he would have them unite with in Love, but the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, againſt whom all the Lovers of Chriſt, muſt profeſs irreconcilible En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. But in the ſenſe &amp; ſentiments of all ſound &amp; zealous Proteſtants; The deſign of the Work &amp; Worker is to get unto himſelf an acknowledgment of his blaſphemous abſolutneſs, and to advance it over all Laws, in a way, which will be beſt acquieſced in by the People till he be ſo ſtrengthened in it, that he fears no control; To get all the Accepters one way or other to operate with him in his Popish and bloody ends. To get our penal Laws againſt the Subjects and Promoters of Antichriſts Kingdom with the leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction ſtoped and diſabled which by this eſteemed gratious Grant, and grateful Acceptance of it, he hath already effectuated. And now by the ſame meaſures he is encouraged to atchieve the total reſcinding and repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them. In the mean time his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45791:11"/>drift is very viſible, and palpable to increaſe differences, diviſions &amp; animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities amongſt Proteſtants to hyre theſe Presbyterians, whom he calleth more moderate to commend his Clemency, while he is exerciſing it, in pillaging plundering, hunting, apprehending, ſtigmatizing, banishing &amp; killing other Conſcientious Non-conformiſts; To ſtop the mouths of Proteſtants with this morſel of Liberty, while he is filling all the places of power &amp; truſt, with men, devoted to his way, by taking off the penal Laws, diſabling them, &amp; then when all power is in the hands of bloody Papiſts, none shall dare to mutter, againſt the ſetting up of the publick Maſſes. And finally he deſigns to infatuate the body of the Land, &amp; lull them aſleep, by this intoxicating Opium, or at leiſt to lay them by from all oppoſition, till he undermine and overturn the Proteſtant Religion, and eſtablish Poperie &amp; Slavery, which he intends either to accomplish by theſe ſmooth flatteries, by peace to overturn Truth, and by getting the Laws againſt the Popish repealled, to make way for reſcinding theſe for the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: Or rendering them ſecure, as the Zidonians, who dwelt careleſſly, to make his bloody Maſſacring attempts upon the whole body, &amp; what he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to do with the whole, if they come not the full length of Comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, may be ſeen in his outragious beginings with the Weſt of Scotland, <hi>the old butt of his malice</hi> which as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he hath expreſſed his deſire, ſo now it ſeems he deſigns to make a <hi>Hunting-field.</hi> We may ſee through the Tragical Hiſtory of former ages, what wicked and hellish deſign the men of his character have had, in their Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations and Proclamations of pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed favour. It is kwon how Julian the Apoſtate amongſt other devices he uſed to root out Chriſtianity, gave a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration openly to all the different Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, that were among Chriſtians, whereof there were many Heretical in thoſe dayes: And he commenced this curſed contrivance, by calling home the Orthodox Bishops, whom Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius banished, that the Church might be embroiled by a civil war of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention among themſelves, as Sozomen obſerves lib. 5. And in the mean time conniving at, &amp; encouraging the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs outrages of barbarous heathens againſt them, which they thought they were well enough Authorized, in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it would pleaſe the Emperour, which was an unwritten Law to them, which afterwards was followed with a more open faced &amp; declared war againſt all that profeſſed Chriſt; which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly aped by <hi>James</hi> the Apoſtate now for the ſame end. So the Maſſacre of Paris was carried on with the Kings Marrying his Siſter to the King of Navar, a famous Proteſtant Prince, &amp; with many publick &amp; ſolemn Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations &amp; Declarations of favour to the Proteſtant Church, while in the mean time, they were plotting &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring how to Maſſacre them all, whereunto he was inſtigate by <hi>Jezebel</hi> his Wife, though he was forward enough himſelf, his genius leading him that way, &amp; which was carried on by the Duke of Guiſe, as the main leader of theſe Murderers, who ſtill cried out (which was all the Law &amp; reaſon he uſed, for inſtigating theſe bloody Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians to that hellish outrage) <hi>Courage my Fellowes this is the Kings command, It is his expreſs will &amp; pleaſure.</hi> And after butcherig the famous <hi>Coligni,</hi> they went thorow the ſtreets (at the toling of the Royal bell, which was the ſign of that horride perpetration) killing all Proteſtants, without diſtinction of age, ſexe or quality, ſo that in the ſpace of two hours or there about, ten thouſand were cruelly put to death in that City.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45791:11"/>The like villany was committed thorow the reſt or France, &amp; the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of the preſent &amp; almoſt unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralelled perſecution there, with the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny &amp; Treachery of that Bigot Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarian after ſo many Laws &amp; Edicts ſeemingly ſecuring the Proteſtants againſt all fears, may let us ſee, what may be expected of thoſe Princes, who devout themſelves to the luſt &amp; rage of Popish Orders, theſe locuſts come out of the bottomleſs pit. We have alſo a recent inſtance of the cruelty and Treacherie of that fiery litle Tyger the Duke of Savoy, againſt ſome of the relicts of the old Waldenſes in the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of Piedmont, who after ſome ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles received, promiſed unto them the enjoyment of their Religious &amp; civil Liberties, if they would lay down their Armes; But after had got them ſpoyled of their outward defence, he catched many thouſands of them, killing them in Priſons with hunger &amp; cold. And as the Duke of York doth affect much the abſolutneſs of the French Monarch, ſo we may expect no better of him (what ever he promiſe (who can do &amp; undo, by vertue of his declared Prerogative, being as abſolute over promiſes as over Laws) and however many do extol him as a Gratious Prince) then that he shall trace the ſteps of his falſehood, treachery, cruelty &amp; Romish Zeal; That ſo we may have an Inſtance of Babylons deceit &amp; rage acted in Brittain &amp; Ireland, which may make other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, not to be Remembered. They are blind who do not ſee, &amp; ſtupid who have not the ſenſe of the dreadfulneſs of theſe deſigns of this Tolerator, which he thinks to accomplish by this Toleration, unto which it is very ſubſervient &amp; which cannot be counteracted, but very much ſtregthened by this acceptance of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In reſpect of its Fountain, from whence it flowes, &amp; is given forth, a deſpotical &amp; Arbitrarian Domination, outvying &amp; ſurmounting the night of <hi>Otteman</hi> Tyranny. It proceeds from &amp; is refounded on the Leviathan of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Authority, Prerogative Royal &amp; abſolute power, which all are to obey without reſerve. Which is a power looſed from, &amp; above all Laws, only regulable by the Royal luſt, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be owned, by any, who know what Religion or Liberty is, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, to nature, contrary to the ends of all Government, the Glory of God, &amp; the good of humane Societies, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipating all the Intereſts of mankind to the luſt of one impowered to deſtroy all, againſt the exorbitancy whereof, no means are left to prevent its obſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the fountains of Juſtice, and turning all into anarchy &amp; confuſion, inconſiſtent with any ſecurity, People can have, either of Religion or Safety, &amp; ſo cannot be the ordinance of God, nor the perſon aſſuming it, his Miniſter for good; A Lawleſs power making all Laws void, needleſs &amp; uſeleſs, &amp; ſo Tyrannical in <hi>Actu ſignato,</hi> claiming a power <hi>Jure</hi> to Tyrannize when he pleaſes; A power deſtructive to the Peoples Liberties, under which the People cannot be ſecured in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of any thing they have in the world; A power invading the incommunicable prerogative of the Univerſal King, who only is abſolute, whoſe Glory is to have his will, for the Rule of his power. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.3. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 46.10. A power expreſſly condemned as Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny in Scripture. <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.19, 20. <hi>Amos.</hi> 6.12, 13. Which in a word can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be better named nor repreſented under a better notion, than that which the famous &amp; faithful <hi>Mr. Andrew Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> calls it, <hi>The bloody gullie of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power,</hi> as he inveighs againſt it, in the aſſembly 1582. This is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain &amp; foundation of this Toleration, by which indeed, the name &amp; common profeſſion of the Proteſtant Religion,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45791:12"/>may be for a time ſuffered precariouſly <hi>durante beneplacito donatoris,</hi> untill his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure shall be to command the eſtablish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Popery, which then he will expect muſt be complied with without controll. But all avouched adherence to old Proteſtant and Presbyterian prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples is hereby interdicted, ſo all the tenure, that Proteſtants have for their Religion, is only the arbitrary word of an abſolute Dominator, whoſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples oblige him to break it, &amp; his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluteneſs to diſdain to be a ſlave to it. Howbeit it cannot be denyed, that the acceptance of this grant declaredly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from ſuch a power, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly requiring the acknowledgment of it, in the acceptance does, imply the recognizance of this power, that the Granter claims in granting it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In reſpect of its Conveyance, &amp; that is through the conduit of the moſt apparent means of eſtablishing Popery, &amp; ſubverting Proteſtancy, by ſtoping &amp; diſabling all theſe penal Laws and Statutes enacted againſt Papiſts, &amp; leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in force, yea commanding to execute according to their rigor, all laws made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt honeſt Presbyterians, the moſt true &amp; faithful Proteſtants, &amp; ſtoping none of the moſt cruel of them, but emitting more &amp; more barbarous Edicts againſt them; For the moſt cruel, are ſuch as are made againſt Field-meetings, which are hereby left in ful vigor, what mean can be more effectual to deſtroy our Reformation; than to ſuſpend all Laws againſt any, that shall attempt the utter ſubverſion of it, and ratifie all wicked Acts againſt ſuch as would moſt avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly aſſert, or own the obligation of all ſacred bonds to preſerve it? Hence as he hath preſumed by abſolute power to ſuſpend all Laws, made for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of our Religion, ſo by the ſame, when he will, he may repeal all Laws for its eſtablishment. And theſe who approve the one by ſuch an acceptance, cannot diſallow the other, but moſt recognoſce a power in this Tolerator to ſubvert all Laws; And ſo by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting this lawleſs, &amp; Law-ſubverting Liberty, they make themſelves guilty of the palpable breach of the national Covenant, where the Laws are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, which this Toleration ſuſpends; And dreadfully acceſſory to all the ſad effects of this undermining all the legal bulwarks of our Religion.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In reſpect of the nature &amp; extent of it. It is Toleration, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes of evil, for that which is good, cannot be <hi>Tolerated,</hi> under the notion of good, but countenanced &amp; encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged as good. Therefore it reflects upon our Religion, when a Toleration is accepted, which implies ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach; ſeeing it is not ratified as a Right, nor encouraged as a Religion, but To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated under the notion of an evil to be ſuffered. And ſuch a Toleration as maks the Profeſſors of Chriſt, partners in the ſame bargain with Antichriſts Vaſſals, &amp; ſets up the Ark in the place, &amp; under the ſame ſconce with dagon; &amp; the Devils thresholds by the Lords threshold; &amp; whereby a ſluce is open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to let the enemy come in like a flood, none lifting up a Standart againſt them. Since it is a Toleration, not only of Archbishops, Bishops &amp; Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, but of all Quakers and Papiſts, reaching all Idolatrie, blaſphemie, Hereſie: which to accept, is contrary to Scripture, our Confeſſion of Faith, &amp; Catechiſmes, as was shewed above; and clearly inconſiſtent with the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Church of Scotland, with the Covenants, national &amp; ſolemn lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue where we are bound <hi>to extirpate Popery, &amp;c. Preſerve the Reformation, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our Liberties,</hi> &amp; ſo never to accept of a Toleration in its nature &amp; tendency everſive of all theſe precious Intereſts, we are ſworn to maintain.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In reſpect of its conditions, limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45791:12"/>&amp; reſtrictions, by which all the kinds of power, that Chriſt hath ſeated in his Church is invaded, invalidated, &amp; evacuated. As (1) the Dogmatick power, whereby Miniſters are to judge of Truth &amp; Error, in point of Doctrine, according to the Word of God only: this Key is extorted out of their hands, for according to the foreſaid Proclamations, nothing may be taught by the moderate Presbyterian Miniſters, in their To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated Meetings, that can be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by the Court, (according to their will, or their Law, for all is one) <hi>to have any tendency to alienate the hearts of the People, from this incontrollable Tyrant or his Government.</hi> Now by vertue of this condition, they may not doctrinal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover unto People, the affronted wickedneſs of this unparalelled prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative; They may not shew the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of the Laws, nor warn of the evil thereof; They may not teſtifie againſt the introduction of Poperie, nor theſe means that give an inlet unto it; They may not once mention any wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deſign, in all this courſe of a curſed Toleration; They may not teach the obligation of the Covenants; Neither witneſs againſt the breaches thereof ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſly; Nor reprove the publick ſins of the time; Nor warn of the dangers thereof, nor exhort them againſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyances in particular with any courſe eſtablished by Law: For all this may be interpreted by Court Expoſitors, to have a direct tendency to alienat Peoples hearts from the man, &amp; his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Accordingly <hi>Mr. Hardy</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, impriſoned and proceeded againſt, for giving Concional Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt the taking off the penal Laws, &amp; Statutes, which would be thought, could not have offended any Proteſtant. (2) The Diatactik power, whereby the Courts of Chriſt are to decern the circumſtances of the worship of God, as time, place, &amp;c. For or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, decency, &amp; edification, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the general rules of the Word. This power is invaded, the Key of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is wroung out of their hands in like manner; For now the places of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship are determined in the Royal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, which muſt be made known to ſome of the Court Patrons on whoſe warrand they are tyed to depend. What may be the hidden deſign of this intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we know not; we heartily wish &amp; pray, it may not be to do with them, as Jehu with the Prieſts of Baal. In the mean time Fed-meetings for the worship of God, which have been ſignally contenanced of the Lord, are ſeverely interdicted; whereby the Word of the Lord, is bound &amp; bounded; And by the accepters conſent to ſuch a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, the bloody Laws againſt preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the open Fields, where People have freeſt acceſs with convenience &amp; Safety are juſtified; The manner of meeting is alſo reſtricted to be in ſuch a way, as the peace and ſecurity of the Government, may not be endangered, &amp; that they be peaceably &amp; publickly held, yea it is expreſſly required in the Proclamation October. 5th. That all who shall preach, by vertue of this Royal Grant, at any time, or in any place, make intimation of their preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as to time &amp; place, <hi>to ſame one or more of the next privie Council-Lords,</hi> which shall be ſufficient for them, during their abode only: Whereby they not only are engaged to keep the peace with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, or his Lievtenant in all their Meetings, &amp; not only to give acceſſion to all his Clandeſtine Cenſores, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how they keep their Inſtructions; But formally muſt mancipate their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, &amp; the freedom of its exerciſe, to a dependence upon the licenſe of his Truſtees; Which is not only a formal bargaining, with the enemies of Truth and Godlineſs, but a becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Servants, and ſo a forfeiting
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45791:13"/>the honour of being eſteemed, while they continue ſo enſlaved, the faithful and free Servants of Chriſt, eſpecially conſidering how as to the matter of their Preaching alſo, they involve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſuch inconveniencies, that either they muſt forbear ſome part of the Counſel of God, and decline the Teſtimony of this day, or elſe expoſe themſelves as a prey to the luſt of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who hereby have brought them into a hoſe-net. 3. The Critick, or Corrective power, which the Courts of Chriſts have to cenſure Delinquents and abſolve the Penitents, according to the Word of God, is alſo invaded &amp; made void; For not only doth this Toleration robb the Miniſters Tolerat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Accepters, conſent to be robbed of that power of impartial cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring thoſe ſcandals that are Tolerated thereby, &amp; all that make themſelves guilty of complying with the ſame; or have been involved in ſinful ſcandal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous complyances with wicked courſes formerly, ſuch as taking of ſinful Oaths, ſubſcribing of ſinful bonds, paying of ſinful exactions, &amp; other ſcandalous breaches of Covenant; Nor dare theſe that are free of them cenſure or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from among them their guilty Brethren, &amp; ſo ſeparate the clean from the unclean: But alſo invads &amp; uſurps this power, formally, in inveſting the Tolerator with Authority to Inhibite, &amp; diſcharge ſome Miniſters the exerciſe of their office whom the ſtanding Laws of this Church do Authorize, and to allow others whom the Word of God, &amp; Conſtitutions of our Church, require to be laid aſide, &amp; ſuſpended from that function. 4. Finally, the Exouſiaſtick power of trying, ſending &amp; Authoriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing office-bearers in the Church, is made uſeleſs &amp; void by this Toleration; For, however an allowance is pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to keep aſſemblies, &amp; ſend out Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to anſwer the Peoples call; Neither are theſe aſſemblies lawfully conſtitute of, nor free for all that have right to ſit there: Nor is their miſſion of Miniſters nor the Peoples call, of any ſignificancy or value, except inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation be made to this Exotick power of their names, that are to officiate, under this Toleration, &amp; they be found ſuch as pleaſe the Court Patrons, which is the worſt of Patronages, that ever burdened this Church. Hence if a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter were never ſo lawfully ordained, never ſo blamleſs in his perſonal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, never ſo formally appropriate to a particular flock, he cannot exerce his function, in any place, unleſs the next privie Councillor, Sherif, &amp;c. Give their allowance. They will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footh, have the Judging whether he be qualified or not, &amp; if he have not the new <hi>conditio ſine qua non,</hi> that only Qualification of them that are to be To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate, <hi>moderation,</hi> in the Court ſenſe, which is nothing but loathſome luk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs in the things of Chriſt, and Court Loyaltie to a vaſſal of Antichriſt, which is diſloyaltie to Chriſt, he can have no Liberty to exerciſe his Office.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In reſpect of the manifeſt &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold ſcandal of it, we cannot but witneſs againſt the acceptance thereof, ſo offenſive to the generation of the Righteous, ſo dishonourable to God, diſgraceful to the Proteſtant Religion, &amp; prejudicial to the Intereſt thereof. As we would not be accounted unfaithful to Chriſt, yea betrayers of our native Country, &amp; Complyers with the deſign of Antichriſt, who hath alwayes miſchief in his heart, &amp; intends this as a prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, for inducing &amp; enforcing all that are hereby lulled aſleep, either to take on this mark, or bear the mark of his fury hereafter. Hereby forreign Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches may think Scotland is now in a fair way of reconciliation with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, when his harbringers favours is ſo kindly accepted, and it cannot but
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45791:13"/>be very ſtumbling to them to ſee the Miniſters of Scotland, whoſe Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny uſed to be terrible to the Popish, &amp; renowned through all the Proteſtant Churches, purchaſing a Liberty to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, at the rate, of burying &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying the Cauſe in bondage and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, &amp; thus to be laid by from all active &amp; open oppoſition to the deſigns of Papiſts in ſuch a ſeaſon. Alas, ſad &amp; shameful have been the ſcandals gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven &amp; taken, by &amp; from the declining Miniſters of this Churchs heretofore, which have rent and racked the poor Remnant, and offended many both at home &amp; abroad; But none ſo ſtumbling as this, which to the preſent and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding generation, will appear to be a ſuccumbing at length, and yeelding up the Cauſe, and ſurceaſing from any more contending for it, a contemning of former wreſtlings for the ſame, tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to harden and hearten open adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries in their wicked invaſions on our Religion, Laws &amp; Liberties, an ſad evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of being weary of the Croſs of Chriſt, &amp; that they would fain have eaſe upon any terms, &amp; a weakening of the hands, &amp; condemning the practice of theſe that ſuffer, when others are at eaſe.</p>
            <p>Next, as we muſt teſtifie againſt the Accepters of this Toleration, who muſt be interpreted to take it, as it is given, and receive it as convoyed from its foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of abſolute power, through its chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel of an arbitrary Law-diſabling, and Religion-dishonouring Proclamation, with conſent to the ſinfull Impoſitions with which it is tendered; Againſt all which there is no acceſs for a Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, conſiſtent with the improvement of it, it being granted and accepted on theſe very terms, that there shall be no Proteſtation; For if there be, that will be found <hi>an alienating of the hearts of the Subjects from the Government,</hi> which by that Proclamation would be reflected upon: So in a particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, we muſt teſtifie againſt the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſers</hi> for it, who have formally ſaid a Confederacie, and congratulated the Tolerator for this Toleration, &amp; all the miſchiefs he is machinating and effectuating thereby, eſpecially ſeeing they have preſumptuouſly taken upon them to ſend their Addreſſes, <hi>in the name of all Presbyterian Miniſters,</hi> we think it concerns all honeſt men, Zealous Chriſtians and faithful Miniſters of that perſwaſion &amp; denomination, in honour &amp; Conſcience to declare to the world by ſome publick Teſtimony, that they are not Conſenters to that ſinful, shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſcandalous conſpiracy, with which, all will be interpreted Conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that are not Contradicters, and charged with the guilt of it, that doth not make the reſentment of it notour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We cannot expreſs with what horror and ſorrow, our hearts were filled to ſee an Addreſs in the name of all the Presbyterian Miniſters in Scotland. And another from the Inhabitants of the City of Edinburgh &amp; Cannongate, who call themſelves of the Presbyterian perſwaſion, who having been alwayes forward in a Catechreſtick loyaltie, or ſlaverie of their perſons &amp; Conſciences, are now ambitious, not to behind any in a flattering Profeſſion of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We ſay we are filled with wonder that they should aſſume to themſelves, the name of Presbyterian Miniſters, and give out their Addreſſes in the name of all, &amp; that it was <hi>at their deſire;</hi> when as the contents of it, are clearly contrary to Presbyterian principles, by juſtifying an Antichriſtian uſurper, in undermining Religion, &amp; approving the abrogation of the national, Covenant, confirming the Laws vow diſabled, by thanking the Tolerator for opening a door to introduce Poperie, which we are ſworn to extirpate, by conſenting to limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; reſtrictions, upon the exerciſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45791:14"/>of their Miniſtrie, by accepting of a bounded Toleration, wherein Idolaters and hereticks have the greateſt share, contrary to our Confeſſion of Faith in the places forecited Chap. 2.23. which, notwithſtanding they have inſinuate, that they do owne, wherein either they bewray great inconſiderateneſs in acting ſo contrary to themſelves, or elſe no ſmall impudence, in laying claim to that Confeſſion, which doth ſo condemn their way; Therefore we teſtifie againſt theſe Addreſſers. 1. Becauſe of the ground for which they Addreſs. What can they alledge for this? It is either for the Liberty granted to the exerciſe of their Miniſtry or elſe the Toleration complexely conſidered: If the former, then ſuppoſe they had got a full &amp; free liberty, it would have been, but what was due, &amp; to thank a man for giving what is not his own ſeemeth to inſinuate a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognoſcing a power to him to withhold it; But now their Liberty is loaded &amp; clogged wil ſinful and ſcandalous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, which is litle ground of thanks; If the latter be ſaid, then they give their conſent to ſet up Poperie and Quakeriſme, for theſe are alſo Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, Alſo it is not to be paſſed, that there is nothing in all the Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions concerning this Toleration in the leſt proteſted againſt by the Addreſſers; So we cannot ſee, how they can free themſelves of congratulating their, <hi>cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment benefactor,</hi> for all the woful evils in the foreſaid Proclamations that reſpect their imaginary favour, <hi>more valuable to then</hi> (as they ſay) <hi>than all earthly comforts.</hi> 2. Becauſe of the ſinful &amp; shamful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of the Addreſſes, they ſpeak not a word againſt the openly deſigned Introduction of Poprie, no reſentment of the everſion of Religious &amp; civil Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, no repreſentation of the wrongs ſuſtained under the graſſation of the two Brothers; No Proteſtation againſt the invaſion made upon the power that Chriſt hath ſeated in the Courts of his Church; &amp; conſequently upon his own incommunicable Headship: Not a word of the Covenants, but they are paſſed over in ſilence, as if they were ashamed of them; They ſay nothing of the Reformation, whereunto we once attained, &amp; were ſolemnly engaged. 3. Becauſe of their Lawleſs &amp; illimited loyaltie. This is profeſſed by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Miniſters, <hi>To his Excellent, To his Gracious, &amp; to his Sacred Majeſtie: Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie not to be queſtioned, an intire Loyaltie in Doctrine,</hi> which is in effect diſloyaltie to Chriſt, in not obſerving their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions received from him, but keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſilent at the wrongs done to him, &amp; not declaring againſt the invaſion of his open enemies: <hi>A reſolved Loyaltie in practice,</hi> whereof alſo the Inhabitants of Edinburgh &amp; Cannongate, will have him aſſured: This is no leſs than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying Religion &amp; Liberty, in lying by from any active Teſtimonie and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the open Deſtroyer of both: <hi>A fervent Loyaltie in Prayers,</hi> which we shall not now inſiſt upon, being to ſpeak of them afterward. This <hi>Loyaltie</hi> of theirs, is not a <hi>Chriſtian Loyaltie,</hi> or Profeſſion of ſubjection for Conſcience ſake, to a Miniſter of God for good, who is a terror to evil doers, nor a Presbyterian Loyaltie, to a King as it is qualified in the national and ſolemn League &amp; Covenants; But a ſtupid ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and abſolute allegiance to a Miniſter of Antichriſt, who gives Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to all evil men &amp; ſeducers; A Loyaltie to a Tyrant in his overturning Religion, Laws and Liberties, and protecting &amp; encouraging all iniquity. 4. Becauſe of their ſoulſome flatterie: We need not inſtance how the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in their Addreſs ſay, <hi>from the deep ſenſe they have of his Majeſties gracious and ſurprizing favour, finding themſelves bound in duty to offer their moſt humble &amp; hearty thanks to his Sacred Majeſtie, the favour
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45791:14"/>being to them valuable above all earthly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts:</hi> And how the Inhabitants of the City of Edinburgh and Cannongate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs themſelves; <hi>We cannot find ſuitable expreſſions to evidence our moſt humble and grateful acknowledgements of your Majeſties late gracious Declaration.</hi> The matter were leſs, if they did not ſpeak a lie, for they ſay they are allowed the free &amp; peaceable publick exerciſe of their Religion. Peaceable &amp; publick it is, They know not how long; free it is not, for their Miniſters are bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſinful reſtrictions as is shown above. And again they adde, <hi>could we open our hearts, your Majeſtie would undoubtedly ſee, whet deep ſenſe and true Zeal for your ſervice, ſo ſurprizing and ſignal a favour hath imprinted on our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> &amp;c. This is worſe than flattery: We ſay we need not adduce particular inſtances of their Adulation, for their whole ſtrain is a rapſodie of flatteries more becoming Sycophants and Court paraſites, than Miniſters &amp; Profeſſors that give out themſelves to be of the Presbyterian perſwaſion. 5. If the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes were only ſtuffed with flatteries, it were leſs, but we cannot diſſemble or conceal our horror &amp; aſtonishment at ſome expreſſions; Which (if they come not near the borders of blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie) are Equivocations inconſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ingenuity: The Miniſters <hi>bleſs the Great God, who hath put this in his Royal heart:</hi> Which muſt either be underſtood in that ſenſe, where it is ſaid <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.17. <hi>God hath put in their hearts to give their Kingdom unto the beaſt;</hi> Which they durſt not expreſs to him, whom they Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, neither durſt they bleſs the Lord for it with application to him: And to ſay this with ſuch a reſerved meaning, were odious to Proteſtants, &amp; all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men. Or if they be ingenuous then they bleſs God for putting it in his heart to project all this wickedneſs, diſcovered in the deſign, tendency and nature of this Popish Toleration; which is not far from blasphemy to make the Holy one, the Author of that, which he hath declared his deteſtation of in his word. They further expreſs their reſolution, <hi>by the help of God, ſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean themſelves, as his Majeſtie may find cauſe rather to inlarge than to diminish his favours towards them.</hi> Which upon the matter is either a double Equivocation, or elſe it muſt be underſtood, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to demean themſelves ſo, as that a Zealous Papiſt shall find cauſe to enlarge his favours to them, and shall not find any cauſe of diſpleaſure at them. They know what he maketh criminal againſt others, to wit, their teaching the obligation of our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, the lawfulneſs of defenſive armes, their teſtifying againſt the encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments made upon the Kingly power of Chriſt, &amp; againſt the taking off the penal Statutes that concern Papiſts, &amp; the like pieces of faithfulneſs. And conſequently they reſolve, they shall be as unfaithful and ſilent Miniſters, as ever pleaſed a Papiſt; For if they be faithful, they may be aſſured, he will <hi>find cauſe to diminish his favours towards them:</hi> Now to purpoſe this by the help of God, comes very near the borders of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. The Citizens of Edinburgh and Canongate, do engage <hi>to continue ſtill in their Prayers, for bleſſing his Perſon &amp; Government;</hi> And shew by what Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they plead for it, to wit, that <hi>by the God of Heaven, Kings reign, and Princes decree Juſtice.</hi> Which with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the Perſon whom they Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, is abſurdly impertinent, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to bring it forth as an adulatory equivocation, with a reſerve that they intend only to offer that general pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in Theſi, without application to him, in the mean time, making him believe, they aſſert the divine appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of his Government: Or elſe it hath the appearance of blaſphemie to extend that propoſition to him, which they cannot do, except they turn it thus,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45791:15"/>by the Lord Tyrants reign, &amp; uſurpers decree Juſtice; which to ſay, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Lords preceptive &amp; appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bative will, as that Scripture muſt be underſtood, were a blaſphemous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignitie to the Holy one, with whom ſuch a Throne of iniquitie can have no fellowship, whereof the poſſeſſors are ſet up, but not by him, &amp; he diſwoneth them, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.4.6. Becauſe the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in their Addreſs, diſowne theſe, who avouch an Adherence to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted reformation, &amp; avow an oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to Antichriſtian uſurpers (which they call <hi>promoting diſloyal principles and practices</hi>) humbly beſeching the Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator <hi>not to look upon ſuch as any of their confederacy.</hi> They needed not have been ſo ſolicitous upon this head, for all that abide in the principles and practices of the Church of Scotland, (which they have deſerted) would count it a ſin &amp; ſcandal, laying them obnoxious to the diſpleaſure of the Holy &amp; jealous God and a shameful reproach, expoſing them to the contempt of all of whom they might expect ſympathie, to be rekoned of their aſſociation, who have thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed the Cauſe &amp; the Country. 7. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their mercenary prayers, that are diſagreeable to the will of God: The Miniſters pray for <hi>divine illumination &amp; conduct</hi> (they durſt not ſay <hi>converſion,</hi> for that would have reflected upon the man, either as a wicked man or a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, or both, but they warrily terme, it, illumination &amp; conduct that he might interpret it, to be for light &amp; leading in this Antichriſtian way of his) <hi>with all other bleſſings ever to attend his Perſon &amp; Government;</hi> Therefore they cannot pray for bringing down the Kingdom of Satan, ſeeing they pray ſo heartily for the ſupport of an eminent prope of it: They pray not that God, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move ſuch an abſolute Tyranny, but that <hi>temporal &amp; ſpiritual bleſſings may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it.</hi> And the Loyaliſts of Edinburgh &amp; Cannongate, after their dutiful and faithful aſſurances, <hi>That as they had not been formerly wanting in praying for him</hi> (where we fear they are not wanting in flattering diſſimulation) for ſo refreshing &amp; unexpected a favour (ſo terme they the Toleration) <hi>will much more engage them to offer up their deſires to God, to bleſs his Perſon &amp; Government.</hi> We wonder whence they have the impudence to ſeek of God, that he would bleſs a Government looſed altogether from his Law, and Diametrically oppoſing it, and regulated only by the luſt of an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarian: And after all, that he would Crown ſuch a Popish Zelot, with an incorruptible Crown of Glory in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Can they be ignorant of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed will of God, that ſuch prayers do clash with it ? Can they be unmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of that, which is generally profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Proteſtants, to wit; <hi>That a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt living &amp; dying true to the principles of the Church of Rome, cannot be ſaved.</hi> They would have him to think, that Heaven is to be gotten very eaſily, when after all his Idolatry, Atheiſme, Murder, Tyranny and Treachery (without any word of repentance) he may attain to that Everlaſting Bleſſedneſs: Heaven is not a City for unclean things. How ſuch prayers will find acceptance with God, let any who read the Scriptures Judge.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe conſiderations, having witneſſed againſt the accepting of, and addreſſing for this Toleration, we come now to teſtifie againſt the ſinful &amp; ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous conjunction of that Incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is made up of ſo ſtrange a mixture, ſome having embraced the former Indulgences; ſome having given bond to the Council not to preach, for an indefinite, or a longer or shorter time; Some having ordinarly heard &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated with the curats; ſome having come under ſinful bonds &amp; Oaths to the perſecuting adverſaries, repugnant to the Oath of our Covenants; And others
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45791:15"/>of them, having gone on in ſundry other ſteps of defection, &amp; in no ſmall contradiction to Chriſts more faithful Sufferers &amp; Witneſſes; Admitting alſo ſome to the charge of ruling elders amongſt them, who had habitually complyed with prelacy, &amp; had born the name of that office under the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats and all this without any reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch horrid courſes that the World can hear of: And ſo they are a corrupt mixture of all ſorts of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliers, &amp; Suffers theſe who have gone on in dreadful Apoſtacie, and ſworn the wicked Oaths, even the Teſt it ſelf, to preſent their Children, to the Sacrament of Baptiſme, without any profeſſion of repentance. Now like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, they muſt according to the Royal Proclamation have one common purſe with the Curats, by caſting in their Baptiſme &amp; Marriage money to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, like that in the Proverbs Chap. 1.14. <hi>Caſt in thy lot among us, let us all have one purſe;</hi> But who would regard the will of the Lord muſt regard what followes v. 15. <hi>My ſon walk not thow in the way with them, refrain thy feet from their path.</hi> This confederacie of theirs, is as the conſpiring of the Prophets in the midſt of Jeruſalem, like a roaring Lyon ravening the prey, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.25. Can ſuch a work be of God, and can it ſtand, which hath ſuch a foundation, ſuch a ſuperſtructure, ſuch meaſures &amp; ſuch workers? We muſt in like-manner teſtifie againſt the Conſtitution of their Eccleſiaſtick Meetings, to wit, their Presbytries, Synods &amp; Aſſemblies; In regard that they are made up of ſuch a corrupt mixture of members, who (for the moſt part) by the Word of God, &amp; decrees of our Church, would be ſuſpended, if not depoſed from their office, &amp; brought in as delinquents to undergo cenſure, &amp; not as conſtituent members of a Judicatory; In regard that the Accepters of this Toleration, hold their miniſtry upon a dependence upon the courts of men; And in regard that they carry on a courſe of defection contrary to the Scriptures, our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, &amp; the Acts &amp; Conſtitutions of this Church, And further we teſtifie againſt all that they may conclude that may be any way prejudicial to our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, or corroberating to this courſe of Apoſtacy. And plainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts that whatſoever determinations, Acts or Commiſſions that shall be given by them, may not be interpreted as binding to the Church of Scotland.</p>
            <p>But now to put an end to this ſad &amp; deplorable declamation, which we can ſay with ſome ſingleneſs of heart, that only Zeal for our Maſters Glory, Love to our Brethren involved in ſuch a ſad ſnare, and the exoneration of our own Conſciences, hath extorted from us, having no acceſs in any other way to acquite our ſelves in our duty to them: We muſt ſubjoyne a ſorrowful, but neceſſary conſequential inference; and thereupon ſubſume that we cannot avoid, but are conſtrained in Conſcience to warn all the Zealous and faithful Lovers of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who are deſireous to confeſs Chriſt before men, &amp; to be liſted among his called, choſen &amp; faithful Followers, who muſt ſide themſelves for him now, in adher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Standart when the enemie is coming in like a flood, and the war is declared between Chriſt and Antichriſt, as they would not be involved in this confederacy, and ſo forefeit the hope of his ſanctuary, in a day when he is a ſtone of ſtumbling and a rock of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to both the Houſes of Iſrael, and ſo many are fallen, broken, ſnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and taken, and as they would not be found acceſſory to, nor guilty of the innumerable evils that are either implied in, or do natively follow upon this new way, to come out from among, diſcountenance and withdraw from the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45791:16"/>Promotters, Abetters of, Carriers, on, Concurrers with this courſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, we mean the Addreſſers for, and Accepters of this Toleration, whoſe iniquity we have endeavoured in ſome meaſure here to diſcover. We abhore that principle that we are invidiouſly calumniated with, of caſting off the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie, or diſowning all the Miniſters of the Church of Scotland: We hope all are not, and shall not be ſo far left in this hour of tentation, ſo to abandon the Word of the Lords patience as thus to forget and forgo the hitherto continued Teſtimony for the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted Reformation, by embracing a Toleration ſo plainly and palpably ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive thereof; And doubt not but there are ſome of our dear and Reverend Brethren who dare not concur in this Conſpiracy, who both mourn in ſecret, and are willing to witneſs their diſlike at the ſins and ſcandals of this courſe, (as they find occaſion, whom only Miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation by the induſtry of our Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers does demur from concurring in this Teſtimony: But as for our declin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Brethren, involved in the guilt of this defection, though we reſpect and reverence them in the Lord, as our beloved Brethren, yet out of Love to them, and to the Souls of the People, whom they and we muſt anſwer for; we cannot but witneſs againſt them, &amp; obteſt them in the Bowels of Chriſt, to relinquish this Courſe, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we muſt warn all that would be free of the ſin of it, and eſcape the Judgements, where with it is like to be purſued, to diſcountenance them, while they continue in it. 1. Becauſe by this bargain and Confederacy with the Tolerator, in the acceptance of this his Antichriſtian Toleration, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving upon certain conditions what he gives, complying with what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, obeying what he commands, relying on what he promiſes, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſing in what he offers upon the very terms that he offers it, (which is a formal confederacy) they become in the exerciſe of their Miniſtry the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of men, and bound to pleaſe them; whereby they forefeit the honour of the free Servants of Chriſt <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10. And change the holding of the freedom of their Miniſtry with Changelings, of which ſort it is not good to meddle, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24— 21. <hi>Mr. Durham</hi> in a digreſſion of hearing Miniſters <hi>Revel.</hi> Chap. 1. pag. 55. in quarto: Shews that by pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable defection from the Truth and Commiſſion given to Miniſters in their call, they may forefeit their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and ſo no more are to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Ambaſſadours to Chriſt or Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of his Flock, than a Watchman of the City is to be accounted an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver, when he hath made publick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the enemy, and taken on with him. Seeing then they have made ſuch a palpable defection from the Truth, as is evidenced above, and from the Commiſſion Chriſt hath given them, they ſo far take on with the enemy as to Addreſs him, and accept of his favours, with a ceſſation of the war, they should maintain againſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, they muſt be looked upon <hi>in tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; pro tempore,</hi> as having <hi>Jure</hi> forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the wonted reſpect due to Chriſts faithful Ambaſſadours while they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in that defection. 2. Becauſe they cannot be ſubmitted to, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to the great encroachements, made upon Both the Priviledges of this Church and Liberties of this Kingdom; For they are fixed in ſuch and ſuch places by a warrand from Councillors, Sherifs, &amp;c. And others are diſcharged, they are Authorized to preach there, by a power encroaching on the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Church, and uſurping the freedom of their Miniſtry. 3. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe while they are under this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Liberty, not only muſt they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45791:16"/>keep Truth in bondage, not daring to declare the ſins, ſnares, duties and dangers of the times faithfully, but People are in hazard of being pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from ſome parts of our Covenanted Reformation, by the Loyaltie of their doctrine and prayers, ſavouring more of ſinful complyance with, and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of wicked men, than of Loyalty to, or Zeal for Chriſt as King; And while in the application of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, they condemn ſuch eſſential parts of the preſent Teſtimony, as are the known and received principles of the Church of Scotland, in her beſt &amp; pureſt times; And in the mean time recede, and juſtify their receſſion from their former way of preaching &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing formerly, who uſed to preach up the Reformation, and the obligation of the Covenants, and cry againſt the ſins of the time, and eſpecially the heaven-daring uſurpations of the Court; And uſed to pray againſt the Throne of Iniquity, the Kingdom and Seat of the beaſt, and all that gave their power to the beaſt, to ſupport that tottering Kingdom: But now People muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect another ſtrain in their doctrine, and another ſtyle in their prayers, ſince they received this hyre of Liberty, who to the ſad ſtumbling of many, and obſervation of all are found to have an apparent tincture of Mercenarineſs, while in ſtead of joyning with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant cry of all the elect for venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance againſt Babylon, &amp; the deſtruction of the whore, they pray for all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings upon the Perſon and Government of a chief Pimp of hers, who knows but ere long, by ſuch prayers People may be induced to ſuch a remitting of their Zeal againſt Popery, as to think it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable to pray for the Pope, as well as for a Popish Tyrant. By ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and prayers they may be cauſed to erre from the words of knowledge, and to receive that inſtruction that <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> bids us ceaſe to hear <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.27. Sure it hath a tendency to cauſe divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions &amp; offences contrary to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which we have learned, and therefore ſuch as cauſe them, are to be marked and avoided, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. 4. Becauſe as there are many terrible Charges and Adjurations laid upon Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, in reference to a faithful dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in their Miniſterial function, &amp; a ſuitable Teſtimony concerning the ſin and duty of the time, as is well obſerved by the Iudicious Author of Rectius Inſtruendum Confut. 3. Dial. Chap. pag. 21. So for their negligence &amp; unfaithfulneſs herein, there are many Scripture woes and threatenings thund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered againſt them, and the People for adhering to them, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9.16. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.27, 28. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 14.15, 16. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 23.14, 16. <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.10, 11, 14, 18, 22. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.25. to the end. And therefore as People would not be partakers of the Judgement with which this Toleration will be purſued, we muſt warn them to beware of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to thoſe who are palpably un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful, in not witneſſing againſt, but juſtifying the ſins of this courſe. 5. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Communion with them in theſe circumſtances, will infer a participation of their ſin, being a Communion in Sacred things, which makes the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the bread to be one body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17, 20. And an unequally yoked fellowship to be ſeparated from, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14, 17. Since it is ſuch a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion as in the preſent circumſtances is interpreted to be a Teſſera of incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration with them, and ſign of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of them in this new way of theirs. 6. Becauſe of the ſcandal in countenancing them in this way, it would be foreborn, not only with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their own Conſciences who joyne not with them, but of others alſo, giving non offence, neither to the Jewes, nor Gentiles, nor to the Church
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45791:17"/>Of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.28. &amp;c. <hi>Maſter Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in the forecited diſgreſſion, makes that a reaſon of forbearing joyning with ſome, that it carries offence along with it, in reference to the party joyned with, it proves a ſtrengthening &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming of him, and ſo a partaking of his ſin; In reference to others, it either ſtrengthens them by that example, to caſt themſelves in that ſnare, or it grieves them and makes them ſad, who are tender of ſuch things, and makes all difference of that kind to be thought light of. Since then in the Toleration it ſelf, addreſſing for it, and accepting of it, there is ſuch a manifeſt ſcandal, there muſt alſo be a manifold offence in countenancing thoſe; that are ſo Tolerated and conſent thereunto, it ſtrengthens and confirms them, it ſtrengthens others to incorporate with them, and weakens the hands of theſe that witneſs againſt it. 7. Becauſe our duty to themſelves yea our greateſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Love, we owe to them in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their conviction, does oblige us to withdraw from them to shame them out of their ſin; and not ſuffer it upon them, eſpecially becauſe they are Brethren, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. That walke diſorderly againſt &amp; without the order of their office, &amp; the order of the Church. <hi>Qui quod ſui eſt ordinis atque officii non fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt, &amp; facientes turbant:</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6-14. We plead not here for ſchiſme or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſeparation; only we apply to this preſent Caſe, the conſtant doctrine of Presbyterians; Wherefore we shall here ſubjoyne ſome plain Quotations out of their Writtings, <hi>Mr. Rutherfoord</hi> in his Due Right of Presbyteries, pag. 253. &amp;c. Diſtinguishes a ſeparation from the Church, in her worſt and moſt part, and a reparation from the beſt and leaſt part, and pag. 258. when the greateſt part of a Church makes defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the leſſer part remaining ſound, the greateſt part of the Church are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts. Truth is like life, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tireth from the married members, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heart in caſe of danger. So it is the major part, that hath made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which are to be accounted ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts, and not ſuch who ſtand to their principles, thô they cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply or joyn with the corrupt majority. Apolog. Relat. Sect. 14. pag. 291. ſaith, there may be a lawful withdrawing, where the ordinances and Miniſtry are not caſt at, ſo long as People does not caſt at the Ordinances, but are willing to run many Myles to enjoy them; Nor caſt at the Church, as no Church (thô they ſadly fear that God shall be provoked by that dreadful defection, to give her a bill of devorce) nor at the Miniſtry, for they love theſe that ſtand to their principles dearly, and are moſt willing to hear them either in publick or private. The Grave Author of Rectius Inſtruendum Confut. 3. Dial. Chap. 1. pag. 7. &amp;c. Allows that every ſeparation is not ſchiſme, even from the Church which hath eſſentials, yea and more than eſſentials, if it be from thoſe thô never ſo many, who are drawing back, from any piece of duty and integrity attained, for this is ſtill to be held faſt according to many Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Commands. Next he ſayes, If we ſeparate in that, which a national Church hath commanded us as her members to diſowne by her ſtanding Acts and Authority while theſe from whom we ſeparate, own that corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He aſſerts there likewayes, there is a lawful forbearance of Union and Complyance with Backſliders in that which is of its ſelf ſinful or inductive to it, which is far from ſeparation ſtrictly taken, the commands of abſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from all appearance of evil, and hating the garments ſpotted with the flesh, do clearely include this. He adds many things will warrant ſeparation from ſuch a particular Miniſter or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45791:17"/>which will not warrant ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from a Church national, nor infer it. Laſtly he ſayes there is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded withdrawing from perſons and ſocieties, even in worship: the precepts <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.20. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.40. will clearly import this by conſequence. Surely the Miniſters and Profeſſors adhering to her reformation, muſt be the true Church of Scotland thô the leſſer number. Theſe Souldiers who keep the Generals order, are the true members, not the deſerters of the ſame.</p>
            <p>In the next place, conſidering how our Covenants are ſlighted, the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them forgotten, and they like to be buried in oblivion; We Judge we are neceſſarly called to ſpeak a word of our Covenants national &amp; ſolemn League, deſiring to bleſs the Lord, who put it in the hearts of his People to engage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to enter into Holy Covenants unto his Holy Majeſtie, and one to another in ſubordination to him, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to theſe things, that concern Truth righteouſneſs &amp; Holineſs. And we do teſtifie our cordial approbation of, and real adherence unto theſe memorable engagements, for we are perſwaded in our minds, that it is the duty of People &amp; Nations, who profeſſes the name of the Lord, to enter into Covenant with him. It is the firſt &amp; great Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we should have no other Gods before him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.3, And that we do his Statutes &amp; Judgements, &amp; to avouch the Lord to be our God, &amp; to walk in his wayes, &amp; to keep his Statuts &amp; Commandments, &amp; his Judgments, &amp; to hearken unto his voice, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.16, 17. And whereof we have many notable precedents in the Book of God, of enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into, &amp; renewing the Covenant of Iſrael by <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 29. by <hi>Joshua Chap.</hi> 24. by <hi>Aſa.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. by <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 29. by <hi>Joſiah.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. by <hi>Ezra Chap.</hi> 10. by <hi>Nehem. Chap.</hi> 9.38. <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.29. And we are alſo no leſs convinced in our Conſciences, that the obligation of our Covenants is perpetual &amp; binding upon poſterity: And to confirm this, we shall adde theſe few conſiderations. Theſe engagements are national promiſes, laying in pledge the publick Faith. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly that promiſe of the Jewish nobles &amp; rulers, not to exact uſury of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, would have brought their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, under the curſe if they should have done it, <hi>Nethem.</hi> 5.12, 13. They are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional vowes, whereby they devoted themſelves, &amp; their poſterity to be the Lords People. <hi>Jacobs</hi> vow at Bethel, <hi>that the Lord should be his God, Gen.</hi> 28.21. did oblige all his poſterity virtually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in him, <hi>he found him at Bethel, and there he ſpake with us,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hoſea</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred years after Chap. 12.4. So the Rechabites were bound to obſerve the vow of their Fore-father <hi>Jonadab.</hi> They are national Oaths, &amp; theſe do oblige poſterity, <hi>Joſeph</hi> took an Oath of the Children of Iſrael to carry up his bones to Canaan, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.25. which the poſterity going forth of Egypt in after-ages, found themſelves ſtraitly ſworn to obſerve, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.19. And accordingly buried them in Shechem, <hi>Josh.</hi> 24.32. They are national Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, wherein King, Parliament and People do Covenant with each other to performe their ſeveral &amp; reſpective duties, as to Religion and Liberty: Theſe oblige the poſterity, as Iſraels Covenant with the Gibeonites, <hi>Josh.</hi> 9.15, 19. for the breach whereof many ages after the poſterity was plagued, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.1. They are national atteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God, as witneſs for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity as well as fidelity thereof. Such are theſe Covenants wherein the name of God is invocated as witneſs, and ſo they are called the Lords Covenants, as that which <hi>Zedekiah</hi> brake, &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord punished him. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17. They are national Covenants made with God as party contracting, which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45791:18"/>none can diſpenſe with; Such were the national Covenants of the Lords People renewed by <hi>Joshua, Aſa, Jehoshaphat, Hezakiah Joſiah, Ezrah, Nehemiah:</hi> They are for the matter national Covenants about things moral objectively obliging and ſo perpetual, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 50.5. They are for their ends, which may be all ſummed up in this, preſervation of Religion and Liberty inviolably, becauſe theſe ends are conſtantly to be purſued. They are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional adjurations, under the pain of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional curſe, which doth make the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity that break them obnoxious. They are for their Legality national Laws, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſolemnly Ratified by Parliament, &amp; by the King, and made the foundation of their compact with him, at his inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration, whereby they became among the <hi>leges Regnandi.</hi> They are national Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants of an hereditary nature, like that of Iſrael, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.14, 15. which did oblige, not only the preſent but the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and conſequently the poſterity. Now conſidering theſe things, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the obligation of our Covenants, the rejoiceing that was at the Oaths of God, when they were taken, the ſingular ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations of his ſpirit at that time, and his teſtifying in his Works of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, his approbation of what his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did in theſe things, according to his Word, by his going forth with his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple &amp; their Armies and making the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to fall before them. We cannot but profeſs the ſorrow of our hearts, &amp; teſtifie the abhorrence of our Souls, againſt all the breaches, injuries or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts that have been, or are offered or done to our Covenants national and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn league; which now (Alas) are like to be deſpiſed &amp; buried in forgetfulneſs: Even when now they are not only na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally broken but burnt, and the own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them is declared criminal, by an Act of Queensberries Parliament which makes it a caſe of confeſſion to aſſert their obligation, particularly we teſtifie againſt the ſinful, shameful, &amp; ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous defection of many Miniſters in this point, by their laying by theſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Covenants, forbearing (under this Toleration) to preach plainly the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of them, to diſcover particularly the breaches of them; and to mention them in the engagments, which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of Parents, when they preſent their Children to Baptiſme. Thô at firſt publication of the foreſaid Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, many of them did privately preach againſt it, when there were none to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge it, but being expoſed to the Court cenſores, in their publick and peaceable Meetings, they are ſubmiſſively ſilent. We find the foregeting &amp; breaking of the Covenant of the Lord, lieth under moſt heavy threatenings, &amp; hath been punished with moſt for Judgements, <hi>Levit.</hi> 16.25, 16, 17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.14.15, 19, 21. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 9.8, 9. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 22.8, 9. <hi>Zech.</hi> 5.3, 4. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.5. We cannot ſlight that which the Miniſters of the County Palatine of Lancaſter, in their harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Teſtimony againſt Toleration (of which we have ſpoken before) do ſay in the like caſe, if we shall now caſt by the Covenant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> after we have reaped ſo much fruit &amp; benefite by it, who knowes, but we may be forced to take it up again to ſave our Lives.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, Becauſe Field-Meetings for Goſpel ordinances, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed in freedom and faithfulneſs, which the Lord hath often ſignally own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed &amp; countenanced to the conviction of many, in the converſion, confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, edification, &amp; conſolation of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poor Souls, are now by wicked and ſanguinary Laws (left ſtill inforce, when the righteous Laws againſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts are ſuſpended) interdicted and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged under pain of death: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt teſtifie our abhorence of this cruelty, when others are ſilent at it; And ſignifie alſo our reaſons of endeavouring to maintain theſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45791:18"/>Meetings with reſpect to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency, ſecrecy &amp; ſafety of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to whom we preach: Not daring to truſt theſe, who are thirſting inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiably after bur blood, nor give them ſuch advantage as they are ſeeking to prey upon us, by shutting our ſelves within houſes. And moreover taking our ſelves, to be called indiſpenſibly in the preſent circumſtances, to be as publick or more than ever in our Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for the preached Goſpel, even in the open Fields. We grant that under the Evangelical diſpenſation, there is no place more Sacred than another, to which the worship of God is aſtricted; And that when we are perſecuted in one place, we may flee into another; And that if a Magiſtrate should prohibite one place &amp; leave all other free, we would not ſtrive for a ſpot; If we were only excluded out of one place, and not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded &amp; reſtricted to other places, nor otherwiſe robbed of the Churches pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges. But this is not our caſe, for we are interdicted of all places, and have to do with one, from whom we can take no orders to determine our Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. It is not then the place of Fields or houſes which we contend for. Nor is it that which he mainly oppoſes, but it is the freedom of the Goſpel faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preached, that we are ſeeking to promote and improve, &amp; he ſeeking to ſuppreſs; And therefore as an enemy to the matter &amp; object of theſe Religious exerciſes, which are the eye-ſore of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, he proſecuts with ſuch fury and force, vigor and rage, cruelty and craft. the manner &amp; circumſtances thereof. But for the expediency, and neceſſitie of our continuing to keep up our Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in Fields, in our circumſtances, we offer theſe reaſons. 1. It is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary at all times that Chriſtians should meet together for Goſpel ordinances, whether the Magiſtrate will or not, the Authority of God, their neceſſity, duty and intereſt maks it indiſpeniſible in all caſes; If then there muſt be ſuch Meetings, for ſuch ends, then when they cannot meet within doors, with conveniency and ſafety, they muſt do it without; If they cannot get the Goſpel in houſes, they muſt have it wherever they can, with the freedom &amp; favour of God coſt what it will. 2. theſe Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings muſt be as publick as may be with conveniency and prudence, eſpecially in an evil-time when wickedneſs is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, and a witneſs for Truth ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Then the Meetings of the Lords People, that endeavours to keep clean garments, should be more frequent, publick &amp; avowed. For (1) Then the call of God, by his Word &amp; Works is more clamant, for publick &amp; ſolemn humiliation, in order to avert immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Judgements &amp; impendent ſtroaks from God, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. <hi>Joel.</hi> 2.15, 16. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.2, 6. The way that the Scriptures points out to evite &amp; avert publick Judgements is to make our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment of theſe indignities done to our God, our mourning over them, &amp; our witneſs againſt them, as publick as the ſins are, at leaſt as publick as we can make it, <hi>by a publick pleading for Truth, Iſai.</hi> 59.4. <hi>a publick ſeeking of Truth, Jer.</hi> 5.1.<hi>an avowed valour for the Truth upon the earth, Jerem.</hi> 9.3. <hi>a making up the hedge, &amp; ſtanding in the gape, Ezek.</hi> 22.30. <hi>A pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick pleading with our Mother, Hoſ.</hi> 2.2. Theſe things cannot be done in private, but by way of Teſtimony. (2) The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and end of Meeting for Goſpel ordinances is for a publick Teſtimony for Chriſt, againſt all ſin, and every dishonour done to the Son of God, the preached Goſpel being not only the Teſtimony of Chriſt, but a Teſtimony for Chriſt, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 122.4. <hi>Math.</hi> 24.14. <hi>Revel.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.11. Where ever then the Goſpel is preached, it muſt be a Teſtimony, but it cannot be a Teſtimony, except it be as publick a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45791:19"/>can be. (3) It is the great work of the day to carry the Goſpel, and follow it, and keep it up as Chriſts banner of love over his Friends and the Standart of war againſt his enemies: When now Zion is labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to bring forth as a Woman in travel, and made to go forth out of the City, and to dwel in the Field, and that which will prompt to beat men out in this publick work, muſt be a publick ſpirit, aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at no leſs than Chriſts publick glory, the Churches publick good, the Saints publick comfort, a publick concern for all Chriſts intereſts, a publick ſymphathie with all Chriſts Friends, and a publick declared op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to all Chriſts enemies, which where it is, will put his Zealous Lovers &amp; Votaries to a publick appearance for him, and avowed ſeeking of him. Cant. 3.1, 4. Cant. 5.7. Pſal. 132 5, 6. (4) The Priviledge of the Goſpel to have it in freedom, putitie power &amp; plentie, is the publick concern of all the Lords People preferrable to all other Intereſts, and therefore more publickly, peremptorly and zealouſly to be contended for, than any other Intereſt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: And therefore we muſt reſolve, they shall ſooner bereave us of out hearts blood, than of the Goſpel in freedom &amp; purity, but we cannot contend publickly for it if our Meetings be not publick. (5) The nature &amp; buſineſs of the Goſpel Miniſtrie is ſuch, that it obliges them that exerciſe it to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour all publickneſs, without which they cannot diſcharge the extent of their Inſtructions. Their very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>nes &amp; Titles do inſinuate ſo much, being Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, Heranlds. Ambaſſadours, Watchmen, light that cannot be hid. The Inſtructions given them infer the neceſſity of it, Iſa. 58.1. Iſai. 62.6, 7. Jer. 6.17. Ezek. 2.5, 6. Ezek. 16.2. Ezek. 20.4. Math. 10.17. Theſe things cannot be done in a Clandeſtine way; And therefore now when there is ſo much ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, it muſt be the duty of all faithful Miniſters to be laying out themſelves to the utmoſt, to give a publick Teſtimony againſt all the evils of the time, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of any prohibition to the contrary, in the moſt publick manner, according to the example of all the Faithful Servants of the Lord, both in the Old &amp; New Teſtament, thô it be moſt impiouſly &amp; Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nically Interdicted, yet the Laws of God ſtands unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, &amp; therefore all that have a Trumpet and a Mouth should ſet the Trumpet to the Month, and found a certain found, not in ſecret, for that will not alarm the People, but in the moſt publick manner they can have acceſs; Therefore ſeeing Meeting muſt be as publick as they can be. That they should be in houſes, ſafety will not permit, to us to go to the ſtreets or mercat places, neither ſafety nor prudence will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, what can we do then, but go to the Fields. 3. Keeping of Field Meetings now is not only moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for teſtifying, but a very ſignificant Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in it ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (1) Againſt the Popish toleration: Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Religion both will conclude that this is to be witneſſed againſt by all that will adhere to the Cauſe of Reformation thereby overturned, and reſolve to ſtands in the gape againſt Popetie, thereby to be intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, and will approve themſelves honeſt Patriots, in defending the Laws &amp; Liberties of the Country, thereby ſubverted; Seeing then it muſt be given, it is certainly moſt expedient to do it there, where the meeting is without its Covert, &amp; interdicted by the ſame Proclamation that tenders it; And where the very gathering in ſuch a place, is a Teſtimony againſt it; For to preach in houſes conſtantly &amp; leave the Fields<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> would now be interpreted an homologating the Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that commands preaching to be ſo reſtricted, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with it. (2) It is a Teſtimony againſt that wicked Law, that diſcharges them as criminal, which cannot be lawfully obeyed when in ſome reſpect, it is come to a caſe of confeſſion; For if Daniels caſe, praying with open windowes, when publick prayer was diſcharged under the Pain of death, was a caſe of Confeſſion, then muſt our caſe come near to it; when publick preaching is diſcharged to us under the ſame penaltie: Thô to us, we reckon it as indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſible duty from theſe Scriptures, 1 Cor. 9.16. 2 Cor. 6.4.8, 9. 2 Tim. 4.2. It is equivalent to an univerſal diſcharge of all publick preaching, when that manner of it, is diſcharged, which we can only have with freedom &amp; ſafety, in a way of publick Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; which can be none other in our circumſtances, but in the Fields. (3) It is a Teſtimony for the headship, honour &amp; princely prerogative of Jeſus, which hath been, &amp; is the great Word of his patience in Scotland, and by an unparalelled inſolence encroached upon by uſurpers in our day; ſince in theſe meetings there is a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Declaration of our holding our Miniſtry, and the exerciſe thereof from Chriſt alone, without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence on, ſubordination to, or licenſe from his uſurping enemies, and that we may and will preach in publick, without Authority from them. (4) It is a Teſtimony for our Covenants, national and ſolemn league, the owning whereof, is declared criminal by that ſame Law, that diſcharges theſe Meetings; Since then the owning of theſe Meetings, and our Covenants are both diſcharged together and the owning of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants does oblige to a publick oppoſition againſt the diſchargers, &amp; an avowed maintainance of the Churches priviledges, whereof this in a manner is the only and chief Liberty now left to be maintained, to keep Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings where we may teſtifie againſt them, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence on their Toleration, it muſt follow that theſe Meetings are to be maintained, which only can be in the Fields with conveniency. 4 To give over Field-Meetings altogether, at this time, would be very ſtumbling, born to Friends, who might look on it, as a fainting and ſuccumbing at leaſt in our contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for the Cauſe of Chriſt, as being quite overcome: And to enemies prove very hardening &amp; encouraging in their wicked deſign of banishing all Meetings out of the Land; For certainly it will not terminate upon a ſimple ſuppreſſion of Meetings of this ſort, but further is intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to extirpate all Meetings for Goſpel Ordinances, in which there is any Teſtimony againſt the Antichriſtian Enemy: To comply therefore with ſuch a forbearance of them at this time, would lay a ſtone of ſtumbling before them in theſe their deſigns, when they shall ſee their contrivances ſo univerſally complyed with wherein they might boaſt that at length they had prevailed to put quite away that eye-fore, the freely preached Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But to come to an end, we shall conclude with that pertinent Epilogue of the Miniſters of Lancaſter in England uſed by them in their Teſtimony againſt Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, thus fearing leiſt if we had altogether held our peace, at this time, God might have ſufficiently vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated his Truths by other Inſtruments: But for our baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, judged us unworthy to be entruſted any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, with ſo precious a Treaſure as Truth is; We have therefore choſen rather to approve our ſelves faithful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, thô for ſo doing, we should be never ſo much perſecuted and condemned by men, than by our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſilence, ſeem to be ashamed of Chriſt, his Truth, our Covenants, Reformation, and the faithful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Chriſt in all ages, although thereby we might be aſſured to gain the whole World. And now having diſcharged our Conſciences in this point, however our Actions may be miſconſtrued by ſome, yet knowing that our witneſs is in Heaven, and that God is the righteous Judge, we are hopeful that the Teſtimony of our Conſciences (that herein, we have aimed at nothing. but the Glory of God, the defence of his Truth, the health and recovery of his bleeding &amp; declining Church the caſting ſome diſcountenance upon this woful To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration and to teſtifie our Adherence to our Covenants and Reformation) will abundantly ſupport us againſt the worſt of evils that can befall us, for witneſs bearing to the Truth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45791:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
